the center
中心
defined as a focal point around which
定义为一个焦点，围绕该焦点
any object revolves
任何物体都在旋转
we however define the center to mean
然而，我们将中心定义为
much more
更多
it's where knowledge and ideas form a
这是知识和思想形成的地方
nucleus
核
where dreams intersect with possibility
梦想与可能性交汇的地方
a starting point from which your life
你的人生的起点
can go anywhere
可以去任何地方
this is how we at columbia business
这就是我们哥伦比亚商业的方式
school define the center
学校定义中心
the very center of business
商业中心
here you'll find the center of
在这里你会找到的中心
opportunity
机会
where world-class academics open doors
世界一流的学者敞开大门的地方
to the world's most dynamic place of
到世界上最有活力的地方
business
商业
new york city come learn at the center
纽约市来中心学习
of knowledge
知识的
where top academic minds do leading edge
顶尖学术头脑在哪里发挥前沿作用
research
研究
on the latest business trends and
关于最新的商业趋势和
innovations
创新
be at the center of access where today's
位于当今的访问中心
titans of industry spend
行业支出巨头
every day face time with students and
每天与学生面对面的时间
faculty
师资队伍
discover the center of convergence where
发现收敛中心
finance
金融
fashion media healthcare high tech and
时尚媒体医疗健康高科技
all industries intersect join the center
各行业交叉加入中心
of community
社区的
where high achievers the world over
世界各地的高成就者
share an open exchange of ideas and
分享开放的想法交流
perspectives
观点
dream at the center of entrepreneurship
梦想是创业的核心
where an ivy league business degree
常春藤盟校商业学位在哪里
gives you entree to the world's fastest
让您进入世界上最快的
growing startup environment
不断成长的创业环境
and reach the center of global impact
并到达全球影响力的中心
where a network of over
网络超过
40 000 alumni are creating real change
40 000 名校友正在创造真正的改变
across the planet the very center of
整个地球的中心
business
商业
where all potential converges where
所有潜力汇聚的地方
chances for success
成功的机会
revolve all around a place you just
围绕着一个地方
won't find anywhere else
不会在其他地方找到
come find yourself here at the very
快来发现自己在这里
center of business
商业中心
columbia business school
哥伦比亚商学院
foreign
外国的
live streaming from columbia business
哥伦比亚商业直播
school in new york city my name is bruce
纽约市的学校我的名字是布鲁斯
town
镇
welcome to the final session of the 13th
欢迎来到十三届五中全会最后一次会议
columbia china business conference
哥伦比亚中国商务会议
home to value investing columbia
哥伦比亚价值投资之家
business school is at the forefront of
商学院走在最前沿
the theoretical development and
理论发展和
practices
实践
of value investing given the average
考虑到平均价值投资
change in global dynamics
全球动态的变化
and market uncertainties what are the
以及市场的不确定性是什么
potential advancements
潜在的进步
on unwavering fundamentals of value
坚定不移的价值基础
investing
投资
how should practitioners realize value
从业者该如何实现价值
investing in china
投资中国
joining us today are professor bruce
今天加入我们的是布鲁斯教授
greenward and mr lee liu
格林沃德和刘利先生
professor bruce greenward is the
布鲁斯·格林沃德教授是
founding director of the helpful center
帮助中心创始主任
for graham dodd
格雷厄姆·多德
investing at columbia business school
哥伦比亚商学院投资
his leading voice in value investing
他在价值投资方面的领先声音
mr lilu is the founder and chairman of
lilu先生是公司的创始人兼董事长
himalaya capital
喜马拉雅首都
a multi-billion dollar investment firm
一家价值数十亿美元的投资公司
that primarily focuses on long-term
主要着眼于长期
investment opportunities
投资机会
in asia and the us he's a distinguished
在亚洲和美国，他是一位杰出的
alumnus of colombia and mr leeloo
哥伦比亚校友和 leeloo 先生
currently serves as a member of the
目前担任该协会的成员
board of trustees of columbia university
哥伦比亚大学董事会
professor greenward routinely wins
格林沃德教授经常获胜
plotters for his classes
为他的班级绘制绘图员
and has trained a generation of value
并培养了一代价值
investors including lisa lillu himself
包括丽莎·利卢本人在内的投资者
recently liu has in-depth knowledge
最近刘有深入的了解
about the chinese market
关于中国市场
his insights are trusted by investment
他的见解受到投资的信赖
legends like buffett
像巴菲特这样的传奇人物
and monger now imagine yourself stepping
现在想象一下你自己正在迈步
into the most overcrowded investment
进入最拥挤的投资
classroom
课堂
at one of the best business schools
在最好的商学院之一
across the globe welcome professor
全球欢迎教授
greenwood
格林伍德
and mr lee okay thank you
李先生，好的，谢谢
um i think this is going to be a rare
嗯，我认为这将是罕见的
privilege for
的特权
everybody i've known lee liu now for
我现在认识的所有人李刘
more than 20 years and not only is he a
20多年来，他不仅是
great investor but he's a great
伟大的投资者，但他是一个伟大的人
conversationalist so why don't we just
健谈者所以我们为什么不直接
start out
开始
uh by talking about how your investment
呃，谈谈你的投资方式
philosophy has changed because value
哲学已经改变，因为价值
investing
投资
is after all always an evolving field
毕竟始终是一个不断发展的领域
since you began the field literally i
自从你真正开始这个领域以来我
think i would say
我想我会说
25 years ago 20 years ago or like 28 now
25 年前 20 年前 或者现在 28 年前
time
时间
so how has it evolved so how have you
那么它是如何演变的 那么你又如何
been influenced by people like
受到像这样的人的影响
uh charlie munger and so on yeah go
呃，查理·芒格等等，是的，去吧
ahead
前面
well so uh before i started i just want
好吧，呃，在我开始之前，我只是想要
to uh
到呃
first of all thank you for all the
首先感谢大家的
organizers of this
本次活动的组织者
great conferences i mean i look at the
很棒的会议，我的意思是我看看
uh
呃
the speakers are just really
扬声器真的很
unbelievable so
难以置信如此
uh the uh the quality of the student
呃呃呃学生的素质
has dramatically improved since i was a
自从我成为一名
student there so
那里的学生所以
thank you for all for that wonderful
谢谢你们带来的一切
work of putting together these great
将这些伟大的作品放在一起的工作
conferences
会议
and it just really gave me such a
它真的给了我这样一个
pleasure to be on the same panel with my
很高兴与我的同一个小组
professor
教授
bruce greenwald in fact i got into uh
布鲁斯·格林沃尔德 事实上我进入了呃
uh the this field really because of
呃这个领域真的是因为
uh professor greenwald's class um
呃格林沃尔德教授的课嗯
i think you know basically you
我想你基本上了解你
you got uh buffet to come to uh speak
你有呃自助餐来呃说话
to a student really
对于一个学生来说真的
roughly 28 years ago and it was really
大约28年前，那真的是
out of that first lecture that i really
从第一堂课中我真的
got into this field so thank you so much
进入这个领域非常感谢
and of course i later as a
当然，我后来作为
business group student
商业组学生
i took all of the courses that professor
我修完了教授教授的所有课程
greenblatt offered and learned a great
格林布拉特提供并学到了很多
deal and made a lot of money too so
交易也赚了很多钱
thank you yeah so the philosophy is that
谢谢，是的，所以哲学是这样的
uh it it is it is you know
呃，是的，是的，是的，你知道
relatively simple uh the practice is
比较简单呃做法是
really hard
真的很难
um so i wouldn't say the philosophy
嗯，所以我不会说哲学
really
真的
evolved all that much for me
为我进化了这么多
before i got really exposed to value
在我真正接触到价值之前
investing through
投资通过
buffett's lecture at a bruce greenwald's
巴菲特在布鲁斯·格林沃尔德的演讲
class
类
but i think my whole approach to life
但我认为我的整个生活方式
was
是
pretty much a set along similar lines
几乎是一组类似的线
and so there's not much of a jump for me
所以对我来说没有太大的跳跃
the idea of buying something at a
在某个地方买东西的想法
discount
折扣
or something that really worth more is
或者真正更有价值的东西是
just is simply intelligent
只是很聪明
so i would say almost all intelligent
所以我想说几乎都是聪明的
investing involves some kind of a value
投资涉及某种价值
investing
投资
and now the difference is is that your
现在的区别是你的
focus on values evolves
注重价值观的发展
over time and two different individuals
随着时间的推移和两个不同的人
they tend to focus
他们倾向于集中注意力
different areas of that
的不同领域
for me when i first started
对我来说，当我刚开始的时候
as a value investor this is now 27
作为价值投资者，现在是 27
28 years ago when i lost my first stock
28 年前，当我失去第一支股票时
i don't really know much about uh
我真的不太了解呃
business uh i i know i was born and
商业呃我我知道我出生了
raised in
长大于
uh china during the uh cultural
呃中国在呃文化期间
revolution there was
那里发生了革命
not much of a private business over
没有太多的私人企业
market economy
市场经济
back then so i have to learn everything
那时我必须学习一切
new
新的
uh so uh at the beginning
呃所以呃一开始
uh obviously if look for value uh
呃显然如果寻找价值呃
primarily
主要是
uh on the balance sheet in the in the
呃在资产负债表上
classic uh style of benjamin graham
本杰明·格雷厄姆的经典风格
looking for a cigarette butt uh looking
寻找烟头 呃寻找
for the elastic off
对于松紧带关闭
basically not looking for statistically
基本上不寻找统计数据
cheap
便宜
businesses and ignore what the business
企业并忽略了企业的内容
really is
确实是
and that served me well and that over
这对我很有帮助，结束了
time i evolved
我进化的时间
into understanding smaller businesses
了解小型企业
and because i was just intensively
因为我只是集中精力
curious about how business run
对企业如何运作感到好奇
so much so actually i involved into
这么多，所以实际上我参与了
health funding or co-creating
卫生资助或共同创造
a dozen those early stage startup
十几家早期初创公司
companies
公司
and that experience has taught me a lot
那段经历教会了我很多
about
关于
how businesses what constituted a good
企业怎样才算是好的企业
or bad of mediocre businesses
或平庸企业的坏处
and so over time evolved into looking
所以随着时间的推移演变成寻找
for
为了
really good businesses small maybe but
确实不错的企业，也许规模虽小，但
really good businesses
非常好的企业
uh and then that
呃然后那个
leads me to look for good businesses in
引导我寻找好的企业
asia and eventually
亚洲并最终
for businesses was enduring competitive
对于企业来说具有持久的竞争力
advantage
优势
uh with a long uh growth trajectory
呃，有着很长的呃增长轨迹
ahead
前面
and so the places where we're looking
所以我们正在寻找的地方
for a bad
对于一个坏的
evolves over time but the basic
随着时间的推移而发展，但基本的
philosophy have
哲学有
pretty much remained the same it's just
几乎保持不变，只是
our core competence
我们的核心竞争力
expended over time
随着时间的推移而消耗
now i have been very fortunate to be
现在我很幸运能够
influenced
影响
at the very beginning by the investment
一开始就通过投资
giant
巨人
buffett and and later on i was
巴菲特，后来我是
really really lucky it was just a streak
真的真的很幸运，这只是一次连胜
of uh stroke of a whole lot
呃 一大堆中风
that he can't even make it up uh in
他甚至无法弥补
fictions
小说
that i uh strike a good
我呃打得很好
um connection with uh charlie munger
嗯与查理·芒格的联系
and he become an investor
他成为一名投资者
2003 2004
2003年 2004年
and we've been partners since then
从那时起我们就一直是合作伙伴
basically he has been a mentor
基本上他一直是一位导师
a investor a business partner and a
投资者、商业伙伴和
great friend
好朋友
all those years and for many many years
这么多年，很多很多年
we've been we have dinner every tuesday
我们每周二都去吃晚饭
night
晚上
that's what is my version of a tuesday
这就是我的星期二版本
night with charlie
与查理的夜晚
uh every week uh that lasted
呃每周呃持续
for years until just right around the
多年来，直到大约
pandemic
流行病
and we talk a lot more so obviously i
我们聊了很多所以显然我
had a great deal of influence by him
受他影响很大
but i have to say that the greatest
但我不得不说，最伟大的
influence from charlie was really beyond
查理的影响力确实超出了
just
只是
investment it was he was more of a role
投资，他更多的是一个角色
model in the way he conducted himself in
他以自己的方式行事为人榜样
real life
现实生活
now i think for every profession
现在我认为对于每个职业
everybody
大家
it is wonderful to have role models in
能有榜样真是太好了
life
生活
and often we find role models
我们经常找到榜样
among the imminent dead
在即将死去的人中
because it's safer so it's pretty risky
因为它更安全，所以风险很大
to pick a role model and still still
选择一个榜样并且仍然
alive
活着
and that i always have a risk of
我总是有风险
disappointing
令人失望的
but in my case i got really really lucky
但就我而言，我真的很幸运
in the sense
在某种意义上
that my role model never failed
我的榜样从未失败
in instead of continuing to inspire me
而不是继续激励我
right into his 97th year basically
基本上已经97岁了
and so mostly it's really basic his
所以大多数情况下这是非常基本的
attitude towards
对的态度
life and his ability to keep
生命和他保持的能力
equanimity in a sense in the face of up
某种意义上的平静面对
and downs
和起伏
successful setbacks and i witnessed
成功的挫折和我见证
quite a bit of them
其中相当多
over the 17 years or so we've been
大约 17 年以来，我们一直在
working closely
密切合作
um maintain that rational composure
嗯保持理性的冷静
commonsensical approach to all problems
解决所有问题的常识性方法
investment in our life that is
对我们生活的投资
extraordinary hard
异常艰难
and it is a bit of um
有点嗯
against very natural tendencies
反对非常自然的倾向
and i've really washed the clothes up
我真的把衣服洗好了
close and personal
亲密且私人的
how charlie have conducted himself
查理的表现如何
and it is in that regard that he is
正是在这方面，他是
probably the most influential person in
可能是最有影响力的人
my life
我的生活
and i have been very very lucky in that
我在这方面非常非常幸运
regard
尊重
okay um so in this concentration
好的，所以在这个浓度下
instead of now investing in great
而不是现在投资伟大的
businesses
企业
um can you be specific about
嗯，你能具体说明一下吗
what kind of business you look for what
您寻找什么类型的业务
are the characteristics
是特征
of a great business in particular what
一个伟大的企业，特别是什么
detail characteristics you look for and
您寻找的详细特征以及
how you put a value on those businesses
您如何评价这些业务的价值
yeah well uh great
是啊，呃，太棒了
businesses are the ones who really have
企业才是真正拥有的
above average
高于平均水平
returners as best at capital
回报者最擅长资本
but that kind of businesses socially
但这类企业在社会上
attract
吸引
imitators competitors everybody wants to
每个人都想模仿的竞争对手
have
有
evolved average return to every invested
每笔投资的平均回报率不断变化
capital
资本
and so truly good business is the one
所以真正好的生意就是
who can fend off
谁能抵挡
competitors we can really have enduring
我们真正可以拥有持久的竞争对手
competitive advantage and cap that
竞争优势并加以限制
higher than average return on invested
高于平均投资回报率
capital
资本
and hopefully also have a long runway of
希望也有一条很长的跑道
continuous
连续的
growth those are the businesses we're
增长这些就是我们的业务
looking for
寻找
and they could really come in all
他们真的可以全部进来
industries in all
所有行业
shapes and forms um but they're rare
形状和形式嗯，但它们很罕见
they're really really rare to have a
他们真的很少有
business that generates above average
产生高于平均水平的业务
returns
回报
over a long time on a compounded fashion
很长一段时间以来，复合时尚
this again is really against the natural
这又是非常违背自然的
orders of things
事物的顺序
it really only a small slice of all
它确实只是其中的一小部分
businesses belong to that category
企业属于该类别
so if you're really lucky enough to
所以如果你真的足够幸运
really find one of those
真的找到其中之一
long-term compounders all you have to do
长期复合，你所要做的就是
is really
真的是
uh to own them and own them for the
呃拥有它们并拥有它们
longest period of time
最长的一段时间
now it helps when you really buy them
现在当你真正购买它们时它会有所帮助
at the time when they were happen to be
当他们碰巧在的时候
treated
治疗过的
at a discount to a very intrinsic value
折扣到非常内在的价值
so that if you were wrong about them you
所以如果你对它们的看法是错误的
won't lose
不会失去
money and if you're right you're having
钱，如果你是对的，你就拥有了
more returns over time
随着时间的推移获得更多回报
but over the longest period of time if
但在最长的一段时间内如果
you do own them through the up and downs
你确实拥有它们，经历起起落落
your return roughly approximates
您的回报大致约为
basically
基本上
the actual business return to the actual
实际业务回归实际
capital we invested in the business
我们投资于该业务的资本
itself over the long term
从长远来看
the two to really converge pretty
两者确实非常吻合
closely
密切地
and so understanding and studying the
并因此理解和研究
nature of that business with
该业务的性质
the dynamic but competition is of
充满活力但竞争是
really the most important thing as the
确实是最重要的事情
investor and
投资者和
as a student of the business and as i
作为商科学生和我
said
说
there isn't really a set of things uh
确实没有一套东西呃
that really
那真的
make them that way every business really
让每个企业都如此
builds
构建
their fortress uh slightly differently
他们的堡垒呃略有不同
and you just have to really actually be
你只需要真正做到
honest with yourself and study from
诚实地面对自己并从中学习
every possible angles
每一个可能的角度
until you're really convinced that the
直到你真正确信
azure they're currently enjoying
他们目前正在享受 azure
uh enjoying truly
呃，真正享受
enduring and they truly have a long
持久，他们确实有很长的
runway ahead of them
他们前面的跑道
and if they proved to be exactly as you
如果他们被证明和你一模一样
predicted over the years
多年来预测
we really want to really stay on them
我们真的很想继续留在他们身上
through the up and down they can mean
通过上下他们可以意味着
not to be really this way uh easily
不那么容易就这样 uh
okay can i actually uh talk a little bit
好吧，我可以呃说一点吗
about
关于
those businesses i mean in limiting
我的意思是限制那些企业
competition
竞争
and i think charlie munger is the master
我认为查理·芒格是大师
at this you're really interested in
你对此真的感兴趣
moats
护城河
that is the barriers to entry into the
这就是进入的障碍
business because it's keeping people out
生意，因为它把人们拒之门外
that's going to limit
这会限制
competition if you think about a moat
如果你考虑护城河的话，竞争
there are probably two elements to that
这可能有两个要素
mode so think of it from the point of
模式所以从以下角度思考它
view of a
的视图
company trying to get into the business
公司试图进入该行业
one
一
is economies of scale how big do you
规模经济是指你们有多大
have to get
必须得到
how big a market share do you have to
你需要多大的市场份额
capture in order to be viable
捕获才能生存
as a competitor so in automobiles in the
作为竞争对手，所以在汽车领域
global automobile market it's really
全球汽车市场确实如此
large
大
and if you get one to two percent share
如果你获得百分之一到百分之二的份额
you're going to be fine
你会没事的
in other markets like for example local
在其他市场，例如本地市场
distribution of caffeinated
咖啡因分布
soft drinks you got to get to 20 to 25
软饮料你必须喝到20到25
of the market to support uh the
市场的支持呃
infrastructure that you need
您需要的基础设施
uh and to compete so the first thing is
呃，为了竞争，第一件事就是
economies of scale and the second thing
规模经济和第二件事
i think and again i'm
我想，我又是
sort of thinking about charlie munger
有点关于查理·芒格的想法
here is how hard is it to get that
这就是实现它有多难
mortgage chair which is all about
抵押贷款椅的全部内容
customer captivity in a contested
客户在有争议的情况下被囚禁
environment where
环境所在
unique technology will help you with
独特的技术将帮助您
that and so on so suppose
等等所以假设
you got to get to 25 share we know for
你必须达到我们知道的 25 分享
caffeinated soft drinks
含咖啡因的软饮料
that two tenths of a percent share
十分之二的份额
changes hands every year
每年都会易手
in a contested market so to get to 25
在竞争激烈的市场中达到 25
you're talking about 125 year mode
你说的是125年模式
do you do a calculation like that for
你做这样的计算吗
the companies you're looking at
您正在寻找的公司
you look at those two elements
你看看这两个元素
explicitly
明确地
well that and more okay then what's the
好吧，那更好了，那么什么是
more
更多
the skill is important uh
技巧很重要呃
in there actually there is a scale
那里实际上有一个秤
economy
经济
in those businesses uh not everything
在那些企业中，呃，并不是一切
actually has a skill economy
实际上有技能经济
so sometimes that the skill becomes a
所以有时技能会变成
contract point make it actually more
合同点使它实际上更多
difficult
困难
to really manage um right but
真正管理嗯正确但是
in a scalar economy uh that
在标量经济中呃
the scale does really become a
规模确实成为
competitive advantage
竞争优势
um and then but but the dynamic would
嗯，然后但是但是动态会
have changed
已经改变了
after a certain scale the information
信息达到一定规模后
automobile this
汽车这个
interesting example you know what
有趣的例子你知道吗
happens in
发生在
different phases of the industry um
行业的不同阶段嗯
the uh the the
呃那个
the uh consumer uh aside
呃消费者呃放在一边
is also important in a sense that
从某种意义上说也很重要
if you have um quite a bit of
如果你有很多
uh uh consumer addiction
呃呃消费成瘾
which was certain products and brand
这是某些产品和品牌
loyalty obviously that is important
忠诚度显然很重要
and they're good for a long time until
它们会在很长一段时间内保持良好状态，直到
they're not good
他们不好
um things do change new product
嗯，事情确实改变了新产品
categories would have come along
类别将会随之而来
and run get tired and owed not
跑累了不欠
refreshed need for new generations
新一代的新需求
really don't like to have the same taste
真的不喜欢有同样的味道
as their parents and grandparents so
正如他们的父母和祖父母一样
that's really the most
这真的是最
interesting aspect of businesses is
企业有趣的方面是
is what is only constant is the constant
是唯一不变的就是不变的
change
改变
all great business changes over time
所有伟大的业务都会随着时间的推移而变化
and i absolutely know business it can
我绝对知道它可以做生意
really
真的
remain that competitive edge for
保持竞争优势
forever but some of the business really
永远，但有些生意确实
can keep it
可以保留它
for a very very very long time
很长很长一段时间
and of course when it changes it's
当然，当它改变时
really
真的
upon the management team to be able
管理团队能够
to really we allocate capital towards
真正我们将资本分配给
those businesses actually now we enjoy
现在我们实际上享受这些业务
a robust competitive definition now
现在有一个强有力的竞争定义
taking example with berkshire
以伯克希尔为例
you know starting out as a lousy
你知道一开始是个糟糕的人
businesses losing businesses
失去生意的企业
of texas in new england
德克萨斯州在新英格兰
and warren and charlie skillfully really
沃伦和查理真的很熟练
took the last
拿了最后一个
bit of the cash flow and skillfully
一点点的现金流和巧妙的
invested
投资的
in some other businesses really on the
在其他一些企业中确实
right
对
side of the trajectory but over time
轨迹的一侧，但随着时间的推移
some of those businesses
其中一些企业
began to lose its competitive advantage
开始失去竞争优势
and then they
然后他们
took their capital and they allocated to
他们拿走了他们的资本并分配给
the ones that
那些
so obviously the management capability
管理能力如此明显
of allocating capital
资本配置的
also plays a very important role
也发挥着非常重要的作用
and of course that the culture of
当然，文化
a a company
一个公司
in the industry that's rapidly changing
在快速变化的行业中
so that you always a few step ahead of
让您始终领先一步
your competitors
你的竞争对手
which allows you to always observing on
这使您可以始终观察
the edge
边缘
that also becomes uh enduring
这也变得持久
competitive advantage if that culture
如果这种文化具有竞争优势
endures
忍受
so in every specific businesses
所以在每一个具体的业务中
what really make them successful are
真正让他们成功的是
very very different
非常非常不同
and they change over time and so
它们会随着时间的推移而改变，所以
that is the most fascinating aspect of
这是最令人着迷的方面
of the competitive dynamics and
竞争动态和
also the most fascinating aspect of
也是最令人着迷的一面
being an investor
作为投资者
well how do you today as of today
那么今天你怎么样
how do you do this differently would you
你会如何以不同的方式做这件事
say for most other investors
对于大多数其他投资者来说
are there things that you look at
有没有你看的东西
specifically
具体来说
are there ways that you approach
你有什么方法可以接近
companies now i'll tell you the thing
公司现在我会告诉你这件事
that when i
那当我
started investing with you and i'm
开始和你一起投资，我
honored to say that i made a lot of
很荣幸地说我做了很多
money
钱
doing it that appealed to me was what
做吸引我的事情是什么
you mentioned
你提到
in your introduction which is small but
在你的介绍中虽然很小但是
small businesses
小企业
are or small markets are necessarily
是或小市场是必然的
markets we have to get a big share
我们必须获得很大的市场份额
uh because one firm can dominate and
呃因为一家公司可以占据主导地位并且
that's not something that most
那不是最重要的事情
investors look at so in what other ways
投资者还以哪些其他方式看待这一问题
do you do things differently
你做事的方式有什么不同吗
from most other value investors and
来自大多数其他价值投资者和
investors
投资者
yeah well you're right you're investing
是的，你是对的，你正在投资
with me
和我一起
or you begin to invest thank god you're
或者你开始投资 感谢上帝
still with me
仍然和我在一起
so thank you for continuing to trust in
所以感谢您继续信任
confidence
信心
uh no back then we were looking for a
呃，不，那时我们正在寻找一个
smaller business because those the
规模较小的企业，因为那些
business i feel i can understand them
我觉得我能理解他们
and as we evolve we begin to look for
随着我们的发展，我们开始寻找
bigger
更大
businesses that we can also understand
我们也能理解的企业
that bigger business does come with a
更大的业务确实伴随着
whole set of advantages
全套优势
that if they are right in a sense um
如果他们在某种意义上是正确的
they also come in with a whole bunch of
他们还带来了一大堆
problems and so
问题等等
we're not really looking not just big or
我们并不是真的看起来不仅仅是大或者
medium or small
中或小
size is is one consideration but it's
尺寸是一个考虑因素，但它是
not in the most important
不在最重要的
uh it's certainly not a determining
呃，这当然不是决定性的
factors when we're looking for
当我们寻找的因素
businesses
企业
there are big businesses because of a
有大企业是因为
certain dynamic
一定的动态
dynamics are still growing at a robust
动力仍在强劲增长
pace
步伐
that are becoming even more entrenched
变得更加根深蒂固
as they become bigger and they still
当它们变得更大并且它们仍然
have long runs of
有长期运行的
growth so that just exists
增长，以便存在
you know the most recent phenomena of
你知道最近的现象
the
的
technology platform because of the
技术平台由于
network
网络
network effect some of the business of
网络效应的一些业务
fitting that characteristics
符合该特征
now they don't necessarily always grow
现在它们不一定总是增长
forever
永远
but they have been growing for a long
但他们已经成长了很长一段时间
long time they're likely to continue
很长一段时间他们可能会继续
for some time and so just the
有一段时间了，所以只是
size itself uh is certainly not the most
尺寸本身呃肯定不是最大的
determining factor by
确定因素为
yeah but then what other dimensions do
是的，但是其他维度会做什么
you do things differently today than
你今天做事的方式与今天不同
other investors who are less successful
其他不太成功的投资者
i don't spend my time studying 100
我不会花时间学习100
people doing that
人们这样做
we spend most of our time study uh
我们大部分时间都在学习 呃
industries studying specific companies
研究特定公司的行业
we're looking for the ones we're already
我们正在寻找我们已经在寻找的人
successful try to
成功的尝试
answer what really make them successful
回答真正让他们成功的因素
can that success be continued
这种成功能否继续下去
and some of the time we we have answers
有时我们有答案
and some of the time we don't
有时我们不
we just continue to really study them
我们只是继续真正研究它们
and
和
continue edit until we have an answer i
继续编辑，直到我们得到答案 i
think one thing that really
认为一件事真的
that is always important for us is
对我们来说始终重要的是
this um intellectual uh honesty
这嗯知识分子呃诚实
basically knowing that we really don't
基本上知道我们真的不知道
know
知道
um but we do know and what we don't
嗯，但我们确实知道和不知道什么
in other words if you claim a
换句话说，如果您声称
circle of confidence you have to
你必须建立的信任圈
understand the ash of the confidence
了解信心的灰烬
you have to know what is false and what
你必须知道什么是假的，什么是
is close
很接近
you have to be very honest with yourself
你必须对自己非常诚实
uh
呃
so we really insist on
所以我们真的坚持
knowing inside and out a particular
了解特定的内里和外在
businesses and
企业和
to the point we're able to predict is
我们能够预测的是
outcome
结果
for example in the next 10 years at
例如在未来 10 年
least i want to know
至少我想知道
that the worst case scenario what the
最坏的情况是什么
business
商业
would look like 10 years from now and so
看起来像是10年后
we do have a long-term
我们确实有一个长期的
horizon in terms we can't really predict
我们无法真正预测的地平线
it forever
它永远
but i want to see whether i can predict
但我想看看我是否可以预测
with a very high degree of competency
具有非常高的能力
90 percent of confidence that
90% 的信心认为
at a minimum what the business would
至少是企业想要的
look like
看起来像
in 10 years given all different
10年内给予所有不同的
contingencies
意外事件
and so and and
等等以及
most of the time we don't have an answer
大多数时候我们没有答案
and we just keep
我们只是保留
studying and keep at it and sometimes we
学习并坚持下去，有时我们
study for years and years before
学习多年
we see okay we really get it and then
我们明白了，我们真的明白了，然后
we wait for price to come to our
我们等待价格到达我们的
striking zone
打击区
and a lot of the time they don't and so
很多时候他们不这样做，所以
that
那个
makes our selection very very difficult
让我们的选择变得非常非常困难
and so when we do select them we tend to
所以当我们选择它们时我们倾向于
really own them for a very very long
真的拥有它们很长很长的时间
time
时间
because the businesses they're really
因为他们确实是企业
good
好
um and we really fully understand
嗯，我们真的完全理解
are very rare you know how do you mean
非常罕见，你知道你的意思
when you really do you understand that
当你真正明白的时候
so anything that we would own we would
所以我们会拥有任何我们想要拥有的东西
buy
买
a lot more as they go down and
当它们下降时会发生更多
how do you start yeah if they go down
是的，如果他们倒下了，你要怎么开始
fifty percent is sixty percent seventy
百分之五十是百分之六十七十
right
对
we buy more so that really gives you
我们购买更多，以便真正为您提供
a measure of our definition of whether
衡量我们的定义是否
we understand them
我们理解他们
okay so what about the market today i
好吧，那么今天的市场怎么样？
mean it seems
意思是看起来
highly valued i mean if you look at
高度重视我的意思是如果你看看
fixed income it seems unprecedented
固定收益似乎是前所未有的
uh that said uh does the market today
嗯，这就是说，今天的市场
remind you of any historical periods
提醒您任何历史时期
you've lived through
你经历过
in good ways or bad and would you have
无论好坏，你会吗
advice for anybody on how to navigate
为任何人提供有关如何导航的建议
well we usually don't study too much
嗯，我们通常不会学习太多
about the market
关于市场
except when they're really extreme and
除非他们真的很极端并且
this is what happens to be one of those
这就是其中之一
more extreme period of time
更极端的一段时间
it is truly in many ways somewhere in
从很多方面来说，它确实是在某个地方
unchartered territories
未知领域
uh the amount of liquidity that's been
呃流动资金量
printed
印刷的
and the level of interest rate
和利率水平
um and also the slow pace of the growth
嗯，而且增长速度缓慢
all of those are quite really remarkable
所有这些都非常出色
uh in this time so how do you really
呃，这一次你真的怎么办？
deal with them
对付他们
um we don't
嗯，我们不
necessarily think that history will
必然认为历史会
repeat
重复
and so every time is slightly different
所以每次都略有不同
instead of
而不是
guessing the patterns of history and
猜测历史的模式和
whether they
无论他们
repeat we focus on selecting
重复一遍，我们专注于选择
companies that can really lift through
真正能够渡过难关的公司
the thick and thin
厚与薄
um whatever the environment
嗯，无论环境如何
business will continue somebody would do
生意会继续有人会做
well
嗯
we just want really investing in those
我们只是想真正投资于那些
companies
公司
was incapable of dealing with those
无法处理那些
extraordinary set of uncertainties and
一系列非同寻常的不确定性和
i'll be doing fine
我会做得很好
and how much is management a part of
管理是其中的一部分
that and how do you
那你怎么样
look for managements that have that
寻找有这样能力的管理层
capability
能力
well in a lot of the companies uh the
嗯，在很多公司里
management will make
管理层将使
big differences the culture of those
那些人的文化差异很大
management we're produced will make a
我们生产的管理将做出
big differences
大差异
but in the small set of experiences and
但在一小部分经验和
management really matters almost
管理真的很重要
nothing but the best the strings of
只不过是最好的琴弦
business sell
业务出售
really has a dynamic of his own
确实有自己的动力
that really almost anybody can run it
几乎任何人都可以运行它
and run it
并运行它
well relatively now those
相对来说现在那些
businesses are really rare they're not
企业确实很少见，但并非如此
that many you can probably put them in
你可以把它们放进去那么多
one hand or two hand
一只手或两只手
and so each again i come back to the
所以每次我都会回到
situation
情况
each time is different you have to
每次都是不同的，你必须
really
真的
look for each specific company company
寻找每个特定的公司
in specific ways
以特定的方式
and ask all kinds of appropriate
并询问各种合适的
questions and study them over a long
问题并进行长期研究
period of time in order to really
一段时间才能真正
honestly say that you actually
老实说你实际上
understand them understand them enough
理解他们 足够理解他们
you can predict
你可以预测
the outcome in 10 years even given all
即使考虑到所有因素，10年后的结果
the up and downs in the macro
宏观上的起伏
environment
环境
so you've lived through in your 23 years
所以你在23年里经历了
running himalaya
跑喜马拉雅
a number of major financial crisis the
多次重大金融危机
asia crisis
亚洲危机
in 97 the tech bust in 2000
97年 2000年科技泡沫破灭
the financial crisis in 2008 and
2008年金融危机和
actually last year the code 19
实际上去年的代码是19
are situation specific things you learn
是你在具体情况下学到的东西
about managements or companies that you
关于您的管理层或公司
look for
寻找
in those crises yeah
在那些危机中是的
well uh so as you said
嗯，正如你所说
my 24 years of managing him like capital
我像资本一样管理他24年
we have gone through several of those
我们已经经历了其中的几个
big crisis each time when that happens
每次发生重大危机
um it was built as once in a century
嗯，它是百年一遇的
crisis it probably was except it happens
它可能是危机，除非它发生了
uh on the time frame of every five to
呃在每五到的时间范围内
ten years
十年
so the financial
所以金融
market boom and bust is has been
市场繁荣与萧条一直是
a constant phenomenon since the
自成立以来一直存在的现象
beginning of the financial market
金融市场的开始
uh several hundred years ago and and it
呃，几百年前，而且它
was
是
driven by human nature as long as human
只要人类存在，就受到人类本性的驱动
nature remain that way
自然依然如此
it would never change it will always be
它永远不会改变它永远是
with us
和我们一起
now as a product of evolution
现在作为进化的产物
we human are basically
我们人类基本上是
i run not necessarily in a very rational
我跑步不一定很理性
way
方式
now we're we're very good at
现在我们非常擅长
rationalization but we're really not
合理化，但我们确实没有
very good at being rational
非常善于理性
uh so so
呃，一般般
we always are looking for uh is in in a
我们一直在寻找呃在一个
sense we're governed by
感觉我们受其管辖
some instead of a heart
一些而不是一颗心
a hard wired a hard coded um
硬连线 硬编码 嗯
instincts and
本能和
we're looking for a zero sum now and
我们现在正在寻找零和
we're looking for
我们正在寻找
fast money and and then you get
快钱然后你就得到了
really totally scared when things goes
当事情发生时真的非常害怕
against you
反对你
so that's basic sense of agreed and fear
这就是同意和恐惧的基本感觉
would always enjoy uh drive the
永远会喜欢呃开车
financial market up and down
金融市场的起起落落
particularly when it comes to money
尤其是在金钱方面
humans are very
人类非常
funny it tends to evoke
有趣的是它往往会唤起
the primal part of human nature
人性的原始部分
and so so particularly relates to
所以特别涉及到
financial market and security market
金融市场和证券市场
money that that
钱那个
human tendency of the extreme
人类的极端倾向
instincts become more amplified
本能变得更加放大
and more extreme and that's why the
更极端，这就是为什么
financial market from the very beginning
金融市场从一开始
has always been characterized by moon
一直以月亮为特征
and bust and what remains so now how do
半身像和剩下的现在怎么办
you deal with
你处理
uh such a environment that will be
呃 这样的环境就会
constant
常数
well one way to deal with that is to
解决这个问题的一种方法是
anticipate that
预计
always on the corner at all times and
始终在拐角处并且
that's basically our attitude
这基本上就是我们的态度
that financial crisis will happen all
金融危机将会发生
the time
时间
people will always be driven by fear by
人们总是会被恐惧所驱使
euphyrium
真叶藻属
by uh i mean by by
呃，我的意思是
this extreme kind of up and downs
这种极端的起伏
and so we're looking for businesses that
所以我们正在寻找这样的企业
are capable
有能力
of looking at leaning through that
看着倾斜通过那
and even businesses that could really
甚至是那些真正可以
thrive in that
在那方面蓬勃发展
environment it says have a certain
它说的环境有一定的
characteristic of anti-fragile
反脆弱性特征
and so so
如此如此
that up and down becomes somewhat
上下变得有点
friendly for us in the sense that
对我们很友好
when our favorite company is on sale you
当我们最喜欢的公司出售时
know discounted by
知道打折
50 60 70 if we have money
50 60 70 如果我们有钱的话
we'll buy more of it if we don't have a
如果我们没有，我们会购买更多
money it's
钱是
it is a hallmark of a good investor you
这是优秀投资者的标志
can
可以
sit through watching your portfolio down
坐下来看着你的投资组合下降
by 50
and not being affected at all on the
并且完全不受影响
other hand
另一只手
other side of the coin is that you're
硬币的另一面是你
equally unaffected
同样不受影响
when everybody around you are making
当你周围的每个人都在做
fast money
快钱
fast and furious a lot of them now
现在很多人都速度与激情
you're really
你真的
seemingly totally left behind so
似乎完全被抛在了后面
and that's really part of the
这确实是
temperament that most
最有气质
people don't have and that's why not
人们没有，这就是为什么没有
everybody can succeed
每个人都可以成功
in this game of the investment and so to
在这场投资游戏中
succeed in this game
在这场比赛中取得成功
and require certain temperament and a
并且需要一定的气质和
certain
某些
understanding of human nature also
也对人性的理解
a certain common sensible approach
某种共同的明智方法
and knowing that they will invest in
并知道他们将投资于
return eventually
最终返回
will mirror the actual business return
将反映实际的业务回报
by actual businesses you know we know in
通过您知道我们知道的实际业务
real life
现实生活
real businesses don't really change by
真正的企业并不会真正改变
day by hour by week
日复一日、一周复一日
by month it took years for them to
他们花了好几年的时间才按月
really
真的
either go up or down and so you should
要么向上要么向下，所以你应该
expect your investment
期待您的投资
without the coming over slowly gradually
没有慢慢地逐渐过来
over a long period of time so the
在很长一段时间内，所以
short-term phenomena should not really
短期现象不应该真正
impact you as much either on the upper
对你的影响同样大
or down
或向下
and so if you have that basic
所以如果你有这个基本的
temperament
气质
and basic approaches what you're going
以及你要做什么的基本方法
to find
找到
is that both of the euphyria as well
是这两个 euphyria 也是如此
as the crush actually can serve you well
因为暗恋对象实际上可以为你提供很好的服务
and this is really going back to ben
这真的又回到了本
graham's basic concept
格雷厄姆的基本概念
of mr market that is there
那里的市场先生
to serve you not to instruct you except
为您服务，不指导您，除非
the real game of the investment
真正的投资游戏
those phenomena both on the up and down
那些向上和向下的现象
tend to be quite extreme
往往相当极端
and testing and so the other thing that
和测试等等其他事情
will be very testing
将会非常考验人
is that you really do need to understand
你确实需要了解
uh the business itself
呃，业务本身
and if you really try to pretend you
如果你真的想假装你
understand
明白
and you're really driven by something
你真的被某件事所驱使
else other than deep understanding
除了深刻的理解之外
you'll be tested and so that's the
你会接受测试，所以这就是
salient nature of the of the financial
金融的显着性质
market and sometimes they almost
市场，有时他们几乎
feel that uh they existed they're too
感觉呃他们存在他们也是
really
真的
to catch human weaknesses uh
抓住人类的弱点呃
that if you really don't understand
如果你真的不明白
something that you pretend to
你假装做的事
you will be busted at some point um
你总有一天会被抓的
but if you truly understand you will be
但如果你真正理解你就会
able to add
能够添加
when the security is really down
当安全状况真的很差的时候
50 60 70 yeah can i actually
50 60 70 是的，我真的可以吗
um talk a little bit about a specific
嗯，谈谈一个具体的
example there and
那里的例子和
maybe get you to talk about an example
也许让你讲一个例子
because one of the things that you
因为你的其中一件事
talked about was the stability of these
谈论的是这些的稳定性
companies
公司
and their managements in the face of a
以及他们的管理层面对的
crisis so crisis tells you a lot and the
危机所以危机告诉你很多
one company that obviously
一家公司显然
recently has done extremely well and you
最近做得非常好，你
could see it
可以看到它
is john deere so if you looked at john
约翰迪尔是吗，所以如果你看看约翰
deere in 2000
2000年迪尔
demand fell by 5 and their profit
需求下降了5，他们的利润
margins fell to zero
利润率跌至零
if you look at what happens to them in
如果你看看他们身上发生了什么
you know 1314
你知道1314
demand falls 35 and their profit margin
需求下降 35，利润率下降
stays at roughly half what it was before
大约保持在之前的一半
which is higher than it had been
比以前更高
historically
历史地
so clearly that's a company that's
很明显，这是一家公司
changed and in the face of
改变并面对
sort of catastrophic uh external
有点灾难性的外部
conditions
条件
has gone from doing quite badly to doing
从做得很糟糕变成做得很好
much better
好多了
do you have examples of that from the
你有这样的例子吗
companies you've invested in
您投资过的公司
where you've seen them perform through a
您在哪里看到过他们的表演
crisis
危机
i i do
我我愿意
my 27 28 years of investment that's
我 27 28 年的投资是
the kind of things you'll collect uh but
你会收集的东西呃但是
normally we don't talk about uh specific
通常我们不会谈论呃具体的
companies
公司
but could you share maybe a historical
但你能分享一下历史吗
experience of that so that the students
的经验，让学生
in the audience
在观众席中
might have a sense of what to look for
可能知道要寻找什么
and looking for this stability
并寻找这种稳定性
well bruce we tried this multiple times
好吧，布鲁斯，我们尝试了多次
in your class i know
在你的课堂上我知道
i'm gonna change it very familiar to me
我要改变它对我来说非常熟悉
and there is a simple logic reason why
有一个简单的逻辑原因
we don't do that
我们不那样做
once you achieve a certain uh notoriety
一旦你获得一定的声誉
uh in a certain field uh the people tend
呃在某个领域呃人们倾向于
to really copy that and that's not
真正复制那个，那不是
the behavior we want to encourage uh
我们想要鼓励的行为 呃
instead of gaining people fish it is
不是让人鱼而是
much better to really teach people how
真正教人们如何做要好得多
to fish
钓鱼
okay so let me do one last question
好的，让我做最后一个问题
do you prefer to be a generalist or a
你喜欢成为多面手还是
specialist
专家
investor and would one work better in
投资者，并且会在以下领域工作得更好
the chinese right
中国右派
in the chinese market than another well
在中国市场比其他市场好
in a sense you always want to be a
从某种意义上说，你总是想成为
generalist
通才
uh in terms of a student of businesses
呃，就商科学生而言
and you're interested you know you have
你有兴趣，你知道你有
to have uh
有呃
to be good at this game you have to have
要想擅长这个游戏，你必须具备
the innate intensive curiosity about the
与生俱来的强烈好奇心
business
商业
all kinds of businesses it doesn't mean
各种企业，这并不意味着
you're going to really
你真的会
really get to the bottom of it
真正追根究底
oftentimes you don't
很多时候你不
if you're honest with yourself but by
如果你对自己诚实
the time you really get into the
当你真正进入的时候
companies you really decided to invest
您真正决定投资的公司
you really better become
你真的最好成为
a true specialist and to the point you
真正的专家，并达到您的目的
really know
真的知道
hopefully better than anybody in the
希望比任何人都好
world you can find
你能找到的世界
including the top management team and
包括高层管理团队和
the top management team because they
高层管理团队，因为他们
manage
管理
the company they tend to be deeply
他们往往深入了解的公司
personally
个人而言
vested in their own biases and may not
受自己的偏见影响，可能不会
be able to look at the business
能够看业务
as objectively rationally as you do
和你一样客观理性
so that's a really test so you want to
所以这确实是一个测试所以你想要
be a true
做一个真实的
specialist in the company you chose to
您选择的公司的专家
really invest
真正投资
but you want to be a generalist always
但你总是想成为一名多面手
of business in general so that your core
一般业务，以便您的核心
covenants your circle of confidence can
你的信任圈可以做出的承诺
constantly be
不断地
evolving and the enlarging over time
随着时间的推移不断发展和扩大
if i still really know what i knew when
如果我还真的知道我当时所知道的
i started when i first took your class
当我第一次上你的课时我就开始了
where when you first invest with me
当你第一次和我一起投资时
we were not really anywhere near the
我们实际上并没有接近
results
结果
and we both joined so luckily
我们都很幸运地加入了
that that we continue to expand and we
我们继续扩大并且我们
continue
继续
to learn but on the other hand it is
学习，但另一方面
fascinating
迷人的
to see that how business evolved over
看看业务是如何演变的
the last
最后一个
few decades will continue to evolve in
几十年后将继续发展
the next few decades
未来几十年
and that really makes me feel that boy
这真的让我感觉到那个男孩
i'm lucky
我很幸运
to choose this field that i get paid
选择我获得报酬的领域
to really satisfy my curiosity and to
真正满足我的好奇心
learn
学习
all these great people and great
所有这些伟大的人和伟大的人
enterprises serving society
企业服务社会
so i feel happy every day doing what i
所以我每天都在做我想做的事
do
做
well okay so let's talk about the
好吧，让我们来谈谈
evolution of markets and in particular
市场的演变，特别是
at a 2010 panel at columbia business
在 2010 年哥伦比亚商业论坛上
school you mentioned that asia's role
学校你提到亚洲的角色
in the global financial system was
在全球金融体系中
becoming increasingly important
变得越来越重要
looking back how has asia's mole evolved
回顾亚洲鼹鼠是如何演变的
in the last 10 years and what about
过去 10 年，又如何？
china's role going forward in both the
中国在这两个领域的角色
world's business economy
世界商业经济
and in the financial well
在财务方面
the word is a turnover exactly as we
这个词就是营业额，就像我们一样
predicted in asia
预测在亚洲
indeed to become a lot more important
确实变得更加重要
particularly china in it
尤其是中国在其中
become even more important as i look at
当我看着时变得更加重要
in the next few decades i would say that
在接下来的几十年里我会说
the chinese
中国人
market and asia in general will become
市场和整个亚洲将变得
even more important
更重要的是
the set of dynamics that already set in
已经设定的一组动态
place
地方
will continue to play off in a robust
将继续以强劲的表现
way
方式
so the chinese security market
那么中国安防市场
in general and asia economy
整体经济和亚洲经济
that will become increasingly a very
这将越来越成为一个非常
very important ever more important
非常重要 越来越重要
component
组件
of the global market well all right so
全球市场的情况很好，所以
let me give you some data that i don't
让我给你一些我没有的数据
think is widely appreciated i mean the
认为受到广泛赞赏我的意思是
chinese numbers are obviously
中国的数字很明显
very difficult to interpret at least the
至少很难解释
official numbers
官方数字
and whenever you see that from a company
每当你从一家公司看到这一点时
the data you really want to look at is
您真正想查看的数据是
the data where there's a reliable
有可靠数据的地方
counter
柜台
and the trade data is where there's a
贸易数据是
reliable counterparty because every
可靠的交易对手，因为每个
chinese export
中国出口
has to be an import from another country
必须是从另一个国家进口的
and every chinese import has to be an
每一件中国进口产品都必须是
export from
出口自
another country over the last eight
过去八年的另一个国家
to ten years china trade
致十年中国贸易
has grown by only about two and a half
仅增长了约两倍半
percent a year
每年百分比
that's less than one percent faster than
这比快不到百分之一
u.s
美国
trade what does that say about chinese
贸易这对中国人来说意味着什么
growth i mean that's clearly much slower
我的意思是增长明显慢得多
than the trade growth
比贸易增长
prior say to 2010 2011 uh
之前说的是 2010 2011 呃
and it's if it's fluctuated obviously
如果波动明显的话
but if anything it's been slowing down
但如果说有什么变化的话，那就是速度正在放缓
what does that say about china's future
这对中国的未来意味着什么
well it tells you that the
好吧，它告诉你
characteristic the chinese economy
中国经济的特点
has changed fundamentally you know up
已经从根本上改变了你知道吗
until 10 years ago
直到10年前
what really propels the chinese growth
真正推动中国经济增长的是什么
is
是
has been uh was uh
一直是呃
international trade uh to a certain
国际贸易呃到一定程度
extent
范围
and i would say back in 2010
我想说早在2010年
uh the net trade
呃净贸易
a meeting the export import netted out
会议出口进口净额
was
是
roughly about 9 of gdp
大约占GDP的9
and so china's economy was heavily
所以中国经济严重
dependent
依赖的
on the global market now what happened
全球市场现在发生了什么
is
是
that and they were growing at really
他们的成长速度确实是
double-digit
两位数
growth at the time when the rest of the
当其余的都增长时
globe
地球仪
global economy was growing at
全球经济增长
much much less a fraction of that and so
更不用说其中的一小部分了，所以
at a certain point once you become the
一旦你成为某个时刻
largest treaty
最大的条约
nation uh you can't really the rest of
国家呃你真的不能其余的
the world wouldn't be able to keep up
世界将无法跟上
and the other thing that is happening is
另一件正在发生的事情是
after the
之后
citizens become middle classes
公民成为中产阶级
their demands changes from basically
他们的要求基本上从
just
只是
work saving too into
工作也节省了
really work and saving and consume and
真正工作、储蓄、消费和
it's just also human nature
这也是人性
so roughly around 10 years ago as you
大约 10 年前，就像你一样
point out
指出
the chinese economy has slowly evolved
中国经济缓慢发展
into more of a consumer consumer-driven
更多地以消费者为导向
economy
经济
to the point that interestingly last
有趣的是最后
year was a
那一年是
watershed year in a sense that the
从某种意义上说，这一年是分水岭
retail sales the total volume
零售额 零售总额
of retail sales for the first time
零售额首次
overtaken the united states
超过美国
china was at the largest retail market
中国是最大的零售市场
in the whole world at a six trillion or
全世界有六万亿或
so
所以
us dollars the u.s is roughly 5.5
美元大约是5.5
trillion now
现在万亿
granted that that was a special year
承认那是特殊的一年
in the sense that uh the global pandemic
从某种意义上说，呃全球大流行
ahead other countries hotter than china
领先于其他比中国更热的国家
it's also said that china have done a
据说中国也做了一个
better job
更好的工作
you manage the pandemic but basically
你控制住了流行病，但基本上
the trend is there
趋势就在那里
china is emerging to become the
中国正在成为
most dynamic fastest growing
最具活力 增长最快
consumer market in the whole world
全球消费市场
and that is likely to continue for many
对于许多人来说，这种情况可能会持续下去
many more decades to come and so that
未来几十年
really
真的
make chinese even more attractive
让中国人更具吸引力
to the global economy in terms of people
就人而言对全球经济的影响
who want to sell it
谁想卖掉它
back to the consumers the middle class
回到中产阶级消费者手中
in china and the characteristic of the
在中国及其特点
economy would change
经济将会改变
and would also really provide unique and
并且也会真正提供独特和
interesting opportunities for global
全球的有趣机会
investors
投资者
let me just talk a little bit about that
让我简单谈谈这个
i mean the
我的意思是
thing about retail sales is that it's
关于零售销售的一个问题是
selling goods
the thing about the developed economies
关于发达经济体的事情
is that they're overwhelmingly service
他们的服务非常出色
economies they're not goods economies
它们不是商品经济
and on that dimension it doesn't look
在那个维度上它看起来并不
like
喜欢
china's doing particularly well and as i
中国做得特别好，正如我所言
say
说
the export data you could understand
您看得懂的出口数据
that that would slow down
那会减慢速度
but the fact that the import data has
但事实上，进口数据有
slowed down just as much or more
减慢同样或更多
tells you something about the nature of
告诉你一些关于本质的事情
domestic growth in china
中国国内增长
what about the challenges in the service
服务方面的挑战如何
sector in china
中国的行业
well you're certainly right that at the
好吧，你肯定是对的
current
当前
stage the surface sector has yet to
地面部门尚未进入阶段
become
成为
as powerful and uh dominant
强大且占主导地位
as most of the mature developed
与大多数成熟的开发者一样
economies in the west
西方经济体
and that's really amazing real set of
这真是令人惊奇的真实设定
opportunities right
机会权
for the decades ahead of them and that's
未来几十年
by the way
顺便说一下
not that much different than all the
与所有的没有太大不同
other developed
其他发达的
economy and a comparable stage of the
经济和可比阶段
development state
发展状态
at ten thousand eleven thousand dollars
一万一万一千美元
per capita gdp
人均国内生产总值
which is where china is today and but
这就是今天的中国，但是
even look at the underlying
甚至看底层
dynamics of the various different
各种不同的动态
businesses different performance
企业表现不同
and those consumptions retails and the
以及那些消费零售和
service
服务
are basically the ones that growing the
基本上都是那些增长
fastest
最快
and overall trade internationally still
以及国际贸易总体情况
growing at a robust rate
强劲增长
but not nearly as much as the domestic
但没有国内那么多
side of the economy
经济的一面
and so that's why the their share of the
这就是为什么他们的份额
gdp has gradually began to shrink
GDP逐渐开始萎缩
so domestic consumption becomes far more
所以国内消费变得更多
important
重要的
both goods and the surfaces as we point
正如我们所指出的，货物和表面
out
出
and so that just tells you that a
所以这只是告诉你
different stage
不同阶段
of the economy where it is today so
今天的经济状况如此
where do you see the unique challenges
您在哪里看到独特的挑战
and opportunities instead of finding
和机会而不是寻找
value investment opportunities
价值投资机会
in china well uh
在中国 嗯
the china remains uh i think
我认为中国仍然存在
one of the best market uh if you're a
最好的市场之一，如果你是
valuable investor
有价值的投资者
um in many sense in a sense and the
嗯，在很多意义上，在某种意义上，
market is still somewhat underdeveloped
市场还有些不发达
the market today is not as
今天的市场并不像
representative
代表
as the real economy the way for example
以实体经济方式为例
united states
美国
and so there's a lot of development in
所以有很多发展
that regard
那方面
and the trading and the investors are
交易和投资者是
still not as mature
还是不够成熟
and there's still a mentality of a fast
还有一种快节奏的心态
trading high turnovers which actually
交易高换手率实际上
renders some of the companies
使得一些公司
again going through a faster pace of
再次以更快的节奏
this boom investment
这股投资热潮
again that usually provides bad
这通常会带来不好的结果
opportunities
机会
for those mature patient investors who
对于那些成熟耐心的投资者
truly know
真正知道
what they're doing and also as you said
他们正在做什么以及你所说的
the service sector of economy
经济服务业
when it comes to financial services is
当谈到金融服务时
still yet to be developed
仍有待开发
and china was really right at the stage
中国在这个阶段确实处于正确的位置
when the financial service industry
当金融服务业
actually
实际上
is about to take off in a big way for
即将大规模起飞
many reasons
很多原因
and it just so happens also the chinese
中国人也是如此
government is quite a kin
政府是亲戚
in making macroeconomic policies
在制定宏观经济政策时
quite conducive for the development of
非常有利于发展
the financial service industry
金融服务业
and they began to open up to the global
他们开始向全球开放
firms as well
公司也是如此
in a way they have never done that
以他们从未做过的方式
before so all those
在所有这些之前
confluence of uh factors
呃因素的汇合
really make the market that much more
真正让市场变得更多
attractive today than it was before
今天比以前更有吸引力
yeah can i say something about that
是的，我可以说一下吗
financial services is probably the fifth
金融服务可能是第五位
and sixth largest service sector
和第六大服务业
the biggest is housing by far the second
最大的是住房，其次是住房
biggest
最大的
is medical care the third biggest is
医疗第三大是
education
教育
and the fourth and fifth biggest are
第四和第五大的是
like wholesale and retail
比如批发和零售
distribution and personal services and
分销和个人服务以及
then financial services although in the
那么金融服务业虽然在
us
我们
it's a little higher than that what
比那个高一点
about those sectors in china
关于中国的这些行业
that sector is also growing right but
该行业也在增长，但是
do you see opportunities in absolutely
你绝对看到机会吗
we do housing
我们做住房
we see an opportunity shelter support
我们看到了庇护所支持的机会
basically uh
基本上呃
virtually every industry are going
几乎每个行业都在发展
through a robust
通过一个稳健的
uh uh growing stage um some more than
呃呃成长阶段嗯一些超过
the others
其他人
and even if the industry they're now
即使他们现在的行业
growing as a fast
快速增长
because you'll find interesting
因为你会发现有趣
companies values
公司价值观
and i don't have to you're the boolean
我不需要你是布尔值
for this field
对于这个领域
and so different people tend to focus
所以不同的人倾向于关注焦点
different aspects of
的不同方面
the industries and different aspects of
的行业和不同方面
the growth profile some
增长概况一些
looking value and high growth companies
寻找价值和高成长的公司
some looking
一些寻找
values that moderate growth companies
缓和成长型公司的价值观
some
一些
outlook value in places that doesn't
在没有的地方展望价值
grow at all
完全成长
in fact they're probably declining and
事实上它们可能正在下降并且
they're able to find even bigger markets
他们能够找到更大的市场
so
所以
if you are a true uh uh good investor in
如果你是一个真正的呃呃好的投资者
the sense
感觉
that you can find a bad in everyone but
你可以发现每个人的缺点，但是
you probably
你可能
more capable of finding values
更有能力发现价值
in a dynamically growing economy such as
在动态增长的经济中，例如
china they're still growing at a
中国 他们仍在以
multiple times
多次
of the mature economy in the west and
西方成熟经济体
there's still enormous amount of
仍有大量的
inefficiency
低效率
in this security market so that
在这个安全市场上，
combination of those two
这两者的组合
really make it enticing on top of that
除此之外真的很有吸引力
one
一
whole series of government report i mean
我的意思是整个系列的政府报告
government reform
政府改革
will make those inefficiencies gradually
会逐渐使这些低效率
be more efficient and so that transition
提高效率，以便过渡
offers even more interesting
提供更有趣的
opportunities so this is this is a good
机会所以这是一个很好的
time for global investors and certainly
全球投资者的时间到了，当然
for
为了
us investors as well okay in those
美国投资者在这些方面也不错
terms that as chinese financial markets
作为中国金融市场的术语
are developing
正在发展
do you have certain reforms or other
你们有某些改革或其他措施吗
things you'd be interested in seeing
你有兴趣看到的东西
implemented do you sort of have a
已实施，你有吗
top development that you'd like to see
您希望看到的顶级发展
happen in the china
发生在中国
financial markets or even in the china
金融市场甚至中国
economy well in the sense it's already
从某种意义上说，经济已经很好
happening
正在发生
that's what i mean that the chinese
这就是我的意思，中国人
government and regulator
政府和监管机构
this in the development of the security
这在安全发展中
market
市场
for years and years the chinese security
多年来中国安全
market is not very representative of
市场不太具有代表性
china's economy
中国经济
partially because it really the uh
部分原因是因为它真的呃
the ipo rules are based what they call
首次公开募股规则是基于他们所说的
approval model uh you have to go through
审批模型呃你必须经过
lenses of approval layers of approval
认可的镜头 认可的层次
process in order to be
过程，以便成为
enlisted and so the wild and bustling
入伍如此狂野繁华
are the ones who will be proved
是那些将被证明的人
by government for whatever reason
政府出于任何原因
sometimes
有时
often not really market driven compare
通常不是真正由市场驱动的比较
with other markets such as the united
与其他市场（例如联合航空）
states
州
that it is based on the gradual
它是建立在循序渐进的基础上的
situation based
基于情况
and so as a market rhythm as a result of
因此作为市场节奏的结果
the financial
金融的
market and security market here are
这里的市场和证券市场是
quite representative of the true economy
比较能代表真实经济
and as the chinese economy moving from
随着中国经济从
a export import driven economy
出口进口驱动型经济
into more of consumer demand economy
更多地融入消费需求经济
the entrepreneurial companies with
创业公司与
market
市场
driven dynamics are increasingly play
驱动动力越来越发挥作用
a larger role and therefore this
更大的作用，因此这
financial market have to reflect the
金融市场必须反映
change in dynamics and china that the
动态变化和中国
chinese government is determined
中国政府决心坚定
reform is uh ipo process
改革是呃 IPO 流程
from one of approval process model
来自审批流程模型之一
into one that is much like united states
变成一个很像美国的国家
of
的
registration based model and so
基于注册的模型等
we are probably still early in that
我们可能还处于早期阶段
process
过程
but as that process began to play out
但随着这个过程开始进行
and we will see
我们将会看到
the financial market become more
金融市场变得更加
reflective
反思性的
of the real economy and the other big
实体经济和其他大型经济体
changes that is happening is
正在发生的变化是
that most of the financing are done
大部分融资已经完成
through the banking sectors
通过银行部门
up to the point you know 80 plus percent
直到你知道百分之八十以上
and over time the financing
并且随着时间的推移融资
is best to really do
最好是真正去做
through what they call direct financing
通过他们所谓的直接融资
mostly through market driven dynamics of
主要是通过市场驱动的动力
fixed income equity and central social
固定收益股权和中央社会
and so we see the overall financing
所以我们看到整体融资
model the chinese
模仿中国人
economy from one that is more indirect
来自一种更间接的经济
into more direct and so thus
变得更直接，因此
is the reason for opening up this
是开放这个的原因
financial service
金融服务
company a financial service industry
金融服务业公司
both for domestic players
对于国内玩家来说
and global players as we're seeing that
以及我们所看到的全球参与者
dynamic plays on it over the next
接下来动态播放它
decade or so there will be a lot more
十年左右还会有更多
opportunities
机会
and the financial market will become
金融市场将变得
more mature there will be more
成熟了就会有更多
institutional players coming into it
机构参与者介入
and the financial market science will
金融市场科学将
become
成为
much much bigger than what it is today
比现在大得多
so those are really all bold well for
所以这些真的都是大胆的
investors who truly understand what
真正了解什么的投资者
they're doing basically in china
他们基本上在中国做
yeah let me ask another question in that
是的，让我再问一个问题
connection i mean the thing about a
连接我的意思是关于一个
service economy
服务经济
is that services are overwhelmingly
就是服务是压倒性的
locally produced and concerned
本地生产并受到关注
there are very few global universities
全球大学很少
for example there are very few global
例如，全球范围内很少有
high schools
高中
very few global hospitals um
全球医院很少啊
that means that typically if you look at
这意味着通常如果你看
developed economies
发达经济体
like united states with big service
像美国一样提供大量服务
sectors
部门
the firms which tend to be local the
倾向于本地化的公司
service firms that tend to be local tend
往往是本地化的服务公司
to be locally financed so i
由当地资助，所以我
assume you know that local banks in the
假设您知道当地银行
united states are much more profitable
美国的利润更高
than the big global banks do you see a
与大型全球银行相比，您认为
comparable trend developing in china
中国的可比较趋势
that you can take advantage of
你可以利用
some and some years and some know i
有些几年有些人知道我
wouldn't say that to the
不会对
local banks in the u.s no but i'm just
美国当地银行 不，但我只是
thinking in terms of
思考
local experts within china and
中国本土专家
local service businesses that would
本地服务企业
include of course local banks
当然包括当地银行
yeah well they tend to really know the
是的，他们往往真的知道
local area
当地
but the chinese regulation of banking is
但中国对银行业的监管是
slightly different
略有不同
so there are only roughly about 15 bags
所以大约只有15个包
that really have
确实有
the mandate of being able to take
能够承担的任务
deposit on a national basis
全国性存款
and all the other rest of financial
以及所有其他其余的财务
institutions
机构
are able to really take deposits in a
能够真正吸收存款
very very small
非常非常小
defined well-defined local region under
定义明确的局部区域
their town
他们的城镇
villages cities it's very special and so
乡村城市很特别，所以
the it is a heavily heavily regulated
它是一个受到严格监管的
businesses and so that really gives them
企业，这确实给了他们
almost oligopoly type of a status in
几乎寡头垄断的状态
terms of
的条款
taking deposit which is very important
存款这一点非常重要
of course in terms of the source of
当然从来源来看
capital
资本
so that dynamic is slightly different
所以动态略有不同
than the united states for example
例如比美国
that the license uh
许可证呃
ability to really be able to open the
真正能够打开的能力
bank is
银行是
much much more relaxed in the united
在联合国轻松得多
states
州
than in china as a result
结果比在中国
the the basically the dynamics
基本上是动态的
of the larger national versus local or
更大的国家与地方或
regional
区域性的
banks and other financial institutions
银行及其他金融机构
are more driven by basically the
基本上更多的是由
business dynamics the market dynamics
业务动态 市场动态
and this is very different than in china
这和中国有很大不同
it is driven first and foremost by
它首先是由
regulation
监管
regime and so that makes
政权，所以这使得
the uh a comparison uh of the banks are
银行的比较呃是
really quite different
真的很不一样
uh in china than the united states
呃在中国比在美国
so would a somebody investing in banks
投资银行的人也会如此
in china have to be an expert in chinese
在中国必须是中文专家
regulation
监管
absolutely specialist
绝对专家
[Music]
[音乐]
[Laughter]
[笑声]
if you don't decide to team us anything
如果你不决定与我们合作
i recommend
我推荐
you better become the most knowledgeable
你最好成为最有知识的人
on the planet before you really
在你真正之前在这个星球上
interested really invest in
有兴趣真正投资
all them through the up and downs and
他们都经历了风风雨雨
thicken things
使东西变稠
and if you do understand them they are
如果你确实理解它们，那么它们就是
good
好
it is far more profitable to own them
拥有它们更有利可图
over the long period of time
在很长一段时间内
okay so why don't we talk more broadly
好吧，那我们为什么不更广泛地讨论一下呢？
about new trends in
关于新趋势
value investing so among the many
价值投资如此众多
popular and up
流行及上升
rising technological fields such as 5g
5G等新兴技术领域
bitcoin ai have any of that
比特币人工智能有其中任何一个
has any of that attracted your interest
其中有没有引起您的兴趣
as a value investor and why
作为价值投资者以及为什么
well as i said if you're a investor
正如我所说，如果你是投资者
you really want to find out
你真的想知道吗
what really influenced the change of
真正影响改变的是什么
your companies
你的公司
if there's one big forces
如果有一股强大的力量
that are really quite prominent is the
真正非常突出的是
fast acceleration of technological
技术的快速加速
changes and of course you need to
改变，当然你需要
be well aware of those mega
充分了解那些巨型
technological trends
技术趋势
um it's this current wrong in wave and
嗯，这是当前的波浪错误，
that started
那开始了
uh call it you know 40 50 years was the
呃，你知道 40 50 年是
invention of the semiconductor
半导体的发明
particularly
特别是
the integrated circuit uh that really
集成电路呃那真的
ultimately
最终
led to a personal computer and the
导致了个人计算机的出现
computation collaboration the
计算协作
computation power
计算能力
uh to ordinary citizens and from there
呃，对普通公民，从那里
there's also the evolution of
还有演变过程
communication technologies
通讯技术
and then the invention of the internet
然后互联网的发明
uh somewhat
呃有点
25 30 years ago from there the mobile
25 30年前从那里移动
internet
互联网
so the intersections of compute as well
所以计算的交叉点也是如此
as
作为
in the omnipresent and uh
在无所不在和呃
instantaneous basically communication
基本即时通讯
really led
真正领导
uh to this new phenomena of artificial
呃对于这种新的人工现象
intelligence
智力
and the data economy as a result of it
以及由此带来的数据经济
and so
等等
this wave of technological change over
这波技术变革已经结束
the last
最后一个
40 years has fundamentally altered
40年发生了根本性的改变
the business landscape of all kinds
各类商业景观
basically
基本上
and so whatever kind of investor you are
所以无论你是什么类型的投资者
we do need to be aware of that huge
我们确实需要意识到这个巨大的
changes
变化
and how do you deal with that in a sense
从某种意义上来说你是如何处理这个问题的
what you're
你是什么
investing in businesses that are either
投资于以下任一业务
well insulated from those technological
与那些技术隔离良好
changes
变化
or in companies whose management
或在其管理层的公司
management team are quite capable of
管理团队相当有能力
adaptive
适应性
to those technological changes better
更好地应对这些技术变革
than their competitors
比他们的竞争对手
or in companies that are leading those
或者在那些领先的公司中
changes or enabling those changes
更改或启用这些更改
so that those changes are really on your
这样这些改变就真正发生在你身上
side
侧面
basically so
基本上是这样
now do you have to be a true expert
现在你必须成为一名真正的专家吗
to the point of an engineer i don't
对于工程师来说我不这么认为
think you do
你认为你这样做
but you you do need to be broadly aware
但你确实需要广泛了解
all those big technology changes now if
现在所有这些重大技术变化如果
you happen to be a venture capitalist
你碰巧是一名风险投资家
in those who feel it of course you do
对于那些有这种感觉的人来说，你当然有这种感觉
but if you're
但如果你是
a generalist and study all the
通才并研究所有
businesses
企业
you need to be aware of those trends how
你需要了解这些趋势
does it really impact
真的有影响吗
in the industry and the companies that
在该行业和公司中
you're investigating
你正在调查
so so we are still
所以我们还是
uh really at that in the middle of that
呃，真的在那中间
gigantic wave
巨浪
that started with the invasion of
从入侵开始
a semiconductor by the way you know when
半导体，你知道什么时候
the transistor was indented
晶体管被缩进
well that's a longer i know yeah that
好吧，那是更长的时间，我知道是的
was 1942
1942年
yes yes yes and the first person i
是的，是的，第一个人我
1961 yes yes i'm
1961 是是是我
referring to the time right you get
指的是你得到的正确时间
uh integrated into industry and so
呃融入工业等等
that's you know that really started this
你知道这才是真正开始的
whole revolution
整个革命
that we're actually still in the middle
我们实际上还处于中间
of it and
其中和
the current uh wave of
现在的呃波
neuron network based artificial
基于神经元网络的人工
intelligence is just kind of
智力只是一种
the recent iteration and
最近的迭代和
the data economy uh that as a result of
数据经济呃，由于
it
它
is the newest adaptation
是最新的适配
by industries in response to that
各行业对此的回应
new technology and we're going gonna see
新技术，我们将会看到
more of it
更多的
as time really began to evolve from here
随着时间真正从这里开始演变
do you see opportunities to invest in
你看到投资机会吗
new technologies do you have an example
新技术你有例子吗
maybe
也许
in your past where you did invest
您过去投资过的地方
successfully in a new technology
成功运用新技术
we have in a sense back in in the days i
从某种意义上说，我们回到了我的时代
was trying to really
试图真正
learn about businesses i invested in a
了解我投资的企业
number of startups
初创公司数量
and so i i am fascinated about the
所以我对
technologies
技术
um and today we have somewhat
嗯，今天我们有一些
uh smaller exposure to that
呃，接触较少
but but it is it is fascinating it's not
但它是令人着迷的它不是
really you're not
真的，你不是
interested in technology it's just it's
对技术感兴趣，仅此而已
not that
不是那个
easy to predict or impact because of the
易于预测或影响，因为
pace of a change
变化的步伐
it does require a different aptitude
它确实需要不同的能力
different domain expertise
不同领域的专业知识
and the other thing is we just have
另一件事是我们有
other set of
其他一组
easier opportunities we just happen to
我们碰巧有更容易的机会
be lucky
幸运吧
[Laughter]
[笑声]
yeah well all right so let's talk about
是的，好吧，我们来谈谈
a specific example a lot of smart people
一个具体的例子 很多聪明人
believe that renewable energy
相信可再生能源
is the next big revolution and you've
是下一场大革命，而你已经
done a lot of work
做了很多工作
on battery technology and byd
电池技术与比亚迪
so is that something that you think
你是这么想的吗
about beyond batteries
关于超越电池
what's your outlook for the electrical
您对电气的前景有何看法
vehicle industry say in the next five
汽车行业表示未来五年
years or is it
是几年还是
overheated now where is tesla going
现在过热了，特斯拉要去哪里
[Laughter]
[笑声]
so the car industry is simultaneously
所以汽车行业同时
kind of being impacted by you know
有点受到你知道的影响
four or five big mega trend the
四五大趋势
electrification
电气化
the right sharing and the autonomous
正确的共享和自主
driving
驾驶
and the intelligent design all of those
以及所有这些的智能设计
really going into
真正进入
the industry simultaneously
行业同时
and so that really had attracted more
所以这确实吸引了更多
entrance
入口
and that really heated the competition
这确实让竞争变得激烈
also against the broad background of
也是在这样的大背景下
uh climate change current uh
呃气候变化当前呃
carbon neutral revolution in the sense
意义上的碳中和革命
so
所以
uh as a result the industry that really
呃，结果这个行业真的
haven't lasted for 100 years has really
真的没有持续100年
turned being turned upside down on the
被颠倒过来
other side
另一边
it is a gigantic industry so other than
这是一个巨大的产业，所以除了
housing is probably one of the biggest
住房可能是最大的问题之一
industry
工业
and so the price is also big in the end
所以最后价格也很大
in the process though the competition is
在此过程中，虽然竞争是
going to become
将成为
very very intense still you know
仍然非常非常强烈你知道
it does still have that uh
它仍然有那个呃
characteristic of being
存在的特征
a scale economy as we talk about at the
我们在会上谈论的规模经济
beginning
开始
of our dialogue um so
我们的对话是这样的
the survivors or the winners do
幸存者或胜利者所做的
need to have a certain uh scale
需要有一定的呃规模
in order to really to win in the end and
为了真正赢得最后的胜利
so
所以
it is still early to predict who will be
现在预测谁会成为还为时过早
the ultimate winner
最终的赢家
but it is not early at all to predict
但现在预测还为时尚早
those mega trends are here to stay
这些大趋势将持续存在
so five years there will be far more
所以五年内将会有更多
electric cars sold we have seen the
电动汽车的销售我们已经看到了
european countries began to declare uh
欧洲国家开始宣布呃
a deadline to stop basically
基本停止的最后期限
gasoline-powered
汽油动力
cars china is following that up
汽车中国正在跟进
i think in dual course that we were
我认为在双轨制中我们是
going to see those magnitudes here to
会在这里看到这些幅度
stay
留下来
and five years from now that trend will
五年后这种趋势将
become even more prominent than what it
变得比原来更加突出
is today
是今天
but it is very difficult to predict
但很难预测
the ultimate whenever any continue to
任何时候继续的终极
attract a new entrance at this point
此时吸引一个新的入口
but i do think that the ones that really
但我确实认为那些真正
precise unique
精确独特
technology have the scale
技术有规模
and have the right strategic
并拥有正确的战略
would focus do well do you have a sense
会集中注意力，做得很好，你有感觉吗
of which companies those are
这些是哪些公司
well i bashed one so
好吧，我殴打了一个所以
so i like my money speaker itself
所以我喜欢我的钱音箱本身
but we're not going to be the only one
但我们不会是唯一的
that's a ruby fuel but
那是红宝石燃料但是
it is a gigantic industry okay
这是一个巨大的产业好吗
so in terms of
所以就
value investing education you actually
价值投资教育你实际上
played a big role
发挥了很大的作用
in promoting and advocating
在促进和倡导
value investing from the books to
价值投资从书本到
actually you underwrote in this class
实际上你在这门课上承保了
that we talked about where i went to
我们谈论了我去了哪里
beijing university and i think it still
北京大学我觉得还是
survives
幸存下来
what's your vision for the kind of
你对这方面的愿景是什么
education
教育
that a new investor should embrace and
新投资者应该接受并
where that education might be available
哪里可以提供这种教育
well first of all thank you bruce for uh
好吧，首先谢谢你布鲁斯呃
come to uh
来呃
teach at the beijing university value
在北大任教的价值
investing classes
投资类
that my colleague jeanne channel and i
我和我的同事珍妮频道
started
开始了
uh six years ago and now is six years
呃六年前，现在是六年了
still running and running farewell
仍在奔跑并奔跑告别
and you have played an important role to
你发挥了重要作用
that and i think our
那我认为我们的
original inspiration for that class was
该课程的最初灵感是
really based on pretty much your class
基本上是基于你的班级
and your classes are pretty much
你的课程非常多
inspired and the continuation of the
的启发和延续
bank
银行
and ben graham's class graham and don
和本·格雷厄姆的班级格雷厄姆和唐
and
和
which had among others
其中有
warren buffet as student and i'm your
沃伦·巴菲特作为学生，我是你的
student
学生
there'll be many more much brighter
还会有更多更明亮的
investors coming after us and that's a
投资者追随我们，这是
good thing
好东西
uh so we're trying to really do our part
呃，所以我们正在努力尽自己的一份力量
to really to pass on those that we
真正地传递那些我们
philosophy the thinking
哲学思想
and the practical parts of value
以及价值的实际部分
uh to the uh to the next generation
呃到呃到下一代
in a sense uh so
从某种意义上说，嗯，所以
in terms of like younger uh students
对于年轻的呃学生而言
where you started today
你今天从哪里开始
so i think a few things will be
所以我认为有几件事会
important um
重要的嗯
when i when i talk to young students and
当我和年轻学生交谈时
people who started out
刚开始的人
um trying to get into the field i say
嗯，我想进入这个领域
several things that's important
有几件事很重要
and you to always adopt a owner's
而你总是采用主人的
mentality
心态
and so i like to really ask a
所以我真的想问一个
young student or an analyst or a firm
年轻学生、分析师或公司
basically to imagine
基本上可以想象
all of a sudden that one of your unknown
突然之间，你的一个不知名的人
uncle died and handed over
叔叔去世并移交
100 ownership to the company to you
100 份公司所有权归您所有
and that's the business you're going to
这就是你要做的事
study so any company
研究所以任何公司
think starting point that way and once
以这种方式思考起点
you're really
你真的
kind of a thinking your own 100 percent
100% 属于你自己的想法
of it your mentality is totally
你的心态完全是
different
不同的
so you never know that business existed
所以你永远不知道生意的存在
now you're 100
现在你100岁了
and you have no idea how to run it you
你不知道如何运行它
don't know the people will run it
不知道人们会运行它
what do you do you want to know
你想知道什么
everything everything you can possibly
一切你能做的一切
get your hands on
动手吧
and a lot of the things you know you
以及很多你认识的事情
don't understand you just know the facts
不明白你只知道事实
you don't understand it but that's okay
你不明白，但没关系
you're going to continue to learn
你将继续学习
until you get a hundred of it and even
直到你得到一百个甚至
if then because of the constant change
如果那么因为不断的变化
you're going to continue to evolve your
你将继续发展你的
knowledge of it
对它的了解
now if you adopt that mentality study
现在如果你采用这种心态研究
any businesses
任何企业
you have really started the process of
你已经真正开始了这个过程
becoming
成为
real valuable investor so that's the
真正有价值的投资者，所以这就是
first thing
第一件事
the second thing is you really want to
第二件事是你真的想要
maintain
维持
intellectual honesty and that is
智力上的诚实，即
very very very important you have to be
非常非常非常重要，你必须如此
really honest of what you know what you
对你所知道的事情非常诚实
assume
假设
would you pretend uh subconsciously
你会下意识地假装呃
and what you don't know and how do you
以及你不知道什么以及你如何
really know
真的知道
that one of the things that charlie have
查理拥有的东西之一
talked about
谈到
that i think make the most sense is it
我认为最有意义的是
was that
那是
i'm never entitled to have a view and
我从来没有权利发表意见
two
两个
i could find the smartest people
我能找到最聪明的人
on the planet who took the other side of
在这个星球上谁占据了另一面
that view
那个观点
and i can argue better that
我可以更好地论证
opposition than he does and when i can
比他更反对，当我可以的时候
do
做
that i would be entitled to have a view
我有权发表意见
same thing and applies to
同样的事情并适用于
investing in a sense that intellectual
从某种意义上说，智力投资
honesty
诚实
is a good life philosophy to begin with
是一个美好的人生哲学
it is a critical it is a vital when it
这是一个关键 当它发生时，它是一个至关重要的
comes to investment
谈到投资
because as i said that the security
因为正如我所说，安全
market almost exists to really point it
市场几乎存在真正指向它
to really to find your weaknesses
真正找到自己的弱点
your dishonesty your potential
你的不诚实你的潜力
um your bushy mushy knowledges
嗯，你那浓密的知识
and if you do not really process that
如果你没有真正处理这个问题
fundamental attitude of intellectual
知识分子的基本态度
honesty you'll be destroyed at some
诚实你会在某些时候被摧毁
point during this
在此期间点
uh during your career by the financial
呃在你的职业生涯中受金融
market it was almost designed that way
市场几乎就是这样设计的
to catch you can i can i say something
抓住你我可以说些什么吗
about that because it was better than
关于这一点，因为它比
designed that way
那样设计的
every time you buy a security thinking
每次购买都有安全思考
it's going to do well
会做得很好
somebody else is selling you that
别人正在卖给你
security thinking it's going to do bad
安全人员认为这会造成不良后果
and vice versa and one of you is always
反之亦然，你们中的一个人总是
wrong
错误的
so you better be sure that you're the
所以你最好确定你是
one
一
that's on the right side of that
就在那个的右边
transaction well
交易顺利
it is there is some zero-sum aspect but
存在一些零和方面，但是
not
不
always oh no it's a hundred percent zero
总是哦不，百分百为零
sum
总和
the average return to all investors
所有投资者的平均回报
in any asset class and therefore in all
在任何资产类别中，因此在所有资产类别中
asset classes
资产类别
is the average return to all those
是所有这些的平均回报
assets it brings out just to take a
它拿出的资产只是为了采取
slightly different view
略有不同的看法
but i'm never going to argue against my
但我永远不会反对我的
professors
教授
i'm just going to say let's just agree
我只想说我们同意吧
with disagreement
有不同意见
that's okay okay it is a fair point
没关系，这是一个公平的观点
it is a fair point another thing i would
这是一个公平的观点，我会做另一件事
say
说
is that you you want to really devote as
是你想要真正奉献的
much time
很多时间
as possible uh to a study
尽可能呃去研究
of the history of the businesses
企业的历史
and the history of a great businessmen
以及一位伟大商人的历史
in the past
过去
the more you'll study more companies
你越多就会研究更多的公司
the better you are when it comes to
当涉及到时你就越好
judgment
判断力
on good opportunities and the judgment
良好的机会和判断力
about the fundamental characteristic of
关于基本特征
the company of interest in you
对您感兴趣的公司
and so i see all three things important
所以我认为这三件事都很重要
to
到
start with the 100 owner mentality
从100所有者心态开始
to continue to train yourself to have a
继续训练自己有一个
high degree
高学历
of intellectual honesty and lastly
智力诚实，最后
to be a really a thorough student
做一个真正彻底的学生
of the history of the businesses all
所有企业的历史
three things
三件事
are really going to be very helpful if
如果真的会很有帮助的话
you are beginning
你正在开始
to get into the field of investment
进入投资领域
or you want to really improve your game
或者你想真正提高你的游戏水平
so
所以
that's the mice my advice doesn't
我的建议不是这样的老鼠
understand good advice i'm not going to
了解好的建议我不会
argue with that
与此争论
when you look back over your own career
当你回顾自己的职业生涯时
yeah
是的
are there things that whether at
有没有什么事情是在
columbia business school or in your
哥伦比亚商学院或您的
career since then
从那时起的职业生涯
you would have done differently that
你会采取不同的做法
would have helped you get to where you
会帮助你到达你想要的地方
are today sort of more quickly and more
今天的速度更快、更多
easily
轻松地
yeah well i look
是的，我看起来
back i feel i'm extraordinarily lucky
回来我觉得我非常幸运
and i feel nothing but gratitude
我除了感激什么也没有
i feel lucky to accidentally step
我很幸运不小心踩到了
into uh buff his lecture
加强他的演讲
at your class basically the first time
基本上是第一次在你的课上
he came
他来了
uh i feel extra lucky that uh
呃，我感到特别幸运，呃
when i got into the business and
当我进入这个行业并且
that in a striker relationship um
在前锋关系中
was charlie munger i feel
我觉得查理·芒格是
extraordinarily
非凡地
fortunate to live in a period of time
庆幸生活在一段时光
when both united states and china of
当美国和中国
going through a fundamental economic
正在经历基本的经济
growth and provide enormous amount of
增长并提供大量的
opportunity
机会
that i happen to really know both
我碰巧两者都认识
marketing well and so
营销好等等
i i looking back my career but not
我回顾我的职业生涯但没有
nothing
什么都没有
i feel nothing but really gratitude um
我除了真的很感激之外没有什么感觉
but in terms of uh on the
但就呃而言
[Music]
[音乐]
on the on the on the transition from the
在 上 在 上 从 过渡
u.s to china
美国到中国
so uh i think a lot of people
所以呃我想很多人
such as myself included went through a
包括我自己在内都经历了
period of time to really try to
一段时间去真正尝试
understand
明白
the nature of the chinese economy and
中国经济的性质和
the nature of the chinese market
中国市场的性质
the nature of the chinese company
中国公司的性质
investment in china's companies
对中国企业的投资
so one of the key learnings that i have
所以我学到的关键知识之一
um and it is not that obvious
嗯，这不是那么明显
is the role that the chinese government
是中国政府的角色
play
玩
in that whole question equation if you
在整个问题方程中如果你
have
有
been a successful investor in the united
是联合的成功投资者
states for example or in the developed
例如，在发达国家或地区
market
市场
you tend to come with a set of
你往往会带着一套
assumptions about
关于的假设
the role of the government and the role
政府的作用和作用
of
的
the market participants and
市场参与者和
when you really look into the chinese
当你真正了解中国人的时候
market
市场
that assumptions you will see a lot of
你会看到很多这样的假设
challenges
挑战
and so you might really from time to
所以你可能真的有时会
time arrive to views
到达观看时间
that are inconsistent with your own
与你自己不一致的
experiences
经历
partially because historically the
部分原因是历史上
chinese government
中国政府
and the u.s government the western
和美国政府西方
government perform a
政府执行
very different rules and that's one of
非常不同的规则，这是其中之一
the
的
key aspects of really investing in china
真正投资中国的关键方面
it really requires a much deeper
这确实需要更深入的
understanding
理解
and also systematic comparison
还有系统比较
to get rid of those biases and that's
摆脱这些偏见
why that
为什么那样
you can really get rid of this typical
你真的可以摆脱这种典型的
global investor going to china either
全球投资者也将前往中国
bold ability you fear your enthusiasm
大胆的能力 你害怕你的热情
or basically pessimistic
或者基本持悲观态度
kind of calming collapse of a china type
一种瓷器式的平静崩溃
of a mentality
一种心态的
when things are not going too well and
当事情进展不太顺利时
so
所以
that is the education the most of the
这就是最受教育的
international investors particularly
特别是国际投资者
when it comes to china
说到中国
would have to really go through and that
必须真正经历那
is important
很重要
but bear in mind the other aspect
但请记住另一方面
to understand the chinese economy
了解中国经济
is that the nature of of
这就是...的本质
the modern economy
现代经济
is its ability to generate sustained
是它产生持续的能力
uh compounded economic growth
呃复合经济增长
something that is only recently
最近才发生的事情
emerged as a human phenomena
作为一种人类现象出现
and this is where we we talk about the
这就是我们谈论的地方
zero-sum
零和
versus uh versus a minion type of
与呃与奴才类型的
mentality
心态
now for the longest period of time that
现在最长的一段时间
almost
几乎
all natural or human affairs
所有自然或人类事务
are characterized by cycles in a sense
在某种意义上具有循环特征
that everything goes up cycles you know
你知道一切都会循环往复
born
出生
always increased energy goes from
总是增加的能量来自
you know hot to cold things from order
你可以根据顺序知道冷热食物
to disorder
使混乱
great business has eventually lost his
伟大的企业最终失去了他的
ash so that has been the nature of
灰烬，这就是它的本质
things
东西
and economy going through boom and bust
以及经历繁荣和萧条的经济
but what
但是什么
something unique happened over several
一些独特的事情发生在几个
hundred years ago
百年前
was the beginning of the industrial
是工业化的开始
revolution we began to see this
革命我们开始看到这一点
phenomenon
现象
of continued sustained compounded
持续复合
economic growth and that is
经济增长，即
really when that value investing become
真的当价值投资变成
very important
非常重要
and that's why you'll begin to have a
这就是为什么你会开始有
phenomenal record
惊人的记录
such as the one produced by warren
比如 Warren 制作的那一款
buffett and now by a few
巴菲特和现在的一些人
other people as well the basic
其他人以及基本的
logic behind that as i said over the
正如我所说的背后的逻辑
long term
长期
your investment return is likely to
您的投资回报可能是
approximate
近似
the actual business return of the
的实际经营回报
company invested
公司投资
and so the fact that you're capable of
事实上你有能力
generating that long-term result
产生长期结果
is a reflection of a changing nature
是自然变化的反映
economy
经济
what really drives that phenomenon is
真正推动这种现象的是
something
某事
that is utterly fascinating i literally
这真是太令人着迷了，我从字面上看
spent
花费了
30 40 years thinking about that
30 40 年思考这个问题
until i think i come to a certain
直到我认为我达到了某个程度
knowledge i wouldn't say i really
知识我不会说我真的
don't know at all but i think what
一点也不知道，但我想什么
really produced
真正制作出来的
that phenomena is is
该现象是
a combination of free market
自由市场的结合
enterprise way of organizing social
企业组织社会的方式
economic affairs
经济事务
and combine that one with the invention
并将其与本发明结合起来
of modern science and technology the
现代科学技术的
combination of those two
这两者的组合
produced a modern
产生了现代的
form of economy it is a paradigm shift
经济形式是一种范式转变
so what's happening in china is that
所以中国正在发生的事情是
roughly around 40 years ago
大约40年前
china has really stumbled finally into
中国终于陷入了困境
that
那个
magic formula of free market
自由市场的神奇公式
economy now with chinese characteristics
中国特色经济
of course
当然
along with modern science and technology
随着现代科学技术
and any economy that
以及任何经济体
has really strike a court and
确实已经告上法庭并且
strike that magic magic formula began to
罢工那神奇的魔法公式开始
produce
生产
a phenomenon of compound economic reform
复合经济改革现象
now that has to combine
现在必须结合起来
with the stability of overall political
随着政治大局的稳定
environment
环境
to allow the market to enforce that the
让市场强制执行
new
新的
economy to really release that power
经济真正释放出这种力量
and that is when sustained
那就是当持续
uh economic i mean sustained investment
呃经济我的意思是持续投资
record
记录
can be possible in china it is
在中国是可能的
it's not always there it's not always
它并不总是存在 它并不总是存在
possible
可能
and often it was a zero sum but i think
通常这是零和，但我认为
from that period
从那个时期开始
on that a sustained win-win type of a
持续共赢的模式
compounded
复合的
investment return becomes possible
投资回报成为可能
and i notice that i didn't really
我注意到我并没有真正
include the
包括
political component of it and
它的政治成分和
most of the uh western observers
大多数呃西方观察家
believe that political democracy has to
相信政治民主必须
be part of the
成为其中的一部分
uh uh equation except they forgotten
呃呃方程式除了他们忘记了
that political democracy wasn't there
政治民主不存在
when that phenomenon began to take place
当这种现象开始发生时
in
在
the west in fact the political democracy
西方实际上是政治民主
happened
发生了
later almost as a result but not because
后来几乎是结果，但不是因为
of it anyway so that is another
无论如何，这是另一个
layer of understanding the phenomena of
对现象的理解层
the investment opportunities in china
中国的投资机会
it could be interesting okay so what
这可能很有趣，好吧，那又怎样
about
关于
uh let's just talk briefly in these last
呃，让我们在最后简单地谈谈
eight or so minutes about your personal
关于您个人的八分钟左右
interest
兴趣
so you've devoted efforts to improving
所以你付出了努力去改进
equality and welfare of
平等和福利
asian americans and given the recent
亚裔美国人，并考虑到最近
elevated attention on this community
对这个社区的关注度提高
what are you doing
你在做什么
and planning to do or think ought to be
计划去做或思考应该是
done for that community
为该社区所做的
well i was really like many
嗯，我真的和很多人一样
people from the asian american community
来自亚裔美国人社区的人
and america that was just
和美国那只是
utterly dismayed heartbroken
彻底沮丧心碎
over the last year and a half uh that
在过去的一年半里呃
particularly since the later years of
尤其是晚年以来
the trump administration
特朗普政府
that get worsened because of the
情况变得更糟，因为
pandemic that this new wave of
这场新一波疫情
anti-aging and hate crimes
抗衰老和仇恨犯罪
and by all statistics that incidence
根据所有统计数据，发病率
of racial discrimination against asian
对亚裔的种族歧视
americans has
美国人有
dramatically increased over the last
较过去大幅增加
year and a half
一年半
and full variety of a different reasons
以及各种不同的原因
the pandemics and the trump policies the
流行病和特朗普的政策
u.s china tension
中美紧张局势
and the systematic historical route the
以及系统化的历史路线
surface to say
表面说
that many people in the asian american
很多亚裔美国人
community are living in
社区居住在
fears literally physical fears today
今天的恐惧实际上是身体上的恐惧
after being here for so many years have
在这里呆了这么多年
been such an important
曾经如此重要
part of american experiment uh
美国实验的一部分呃
experiment
实验
and you know particularly to the
你尤其知道
chinese-american
华裔美国人
community you know after 150 years it
150 年后你才知道的社区
feels like the chinese exclusion act has
感觉排华法案已经
come
来吧
back again so
又回来了
so i've been thinking long and hard what
所以我一直在努力思考什么
can we do
我们可以做吗
to change the paradigm now
现在就改变范式
i had a different experiences when i
当我
came to
来到
america i had a wonderful wonderful
美国，我度过了一段美妙的时光
experiences american embraced me
美国人拥抱我的经历
with open warm heart and i have gotten
带着开放温暖的心，我已经得到了
an enormous
一个巨大的
amount of opportunities by columbia
哥伦比亚的机会数量
university
大学
by all the great people that i met a
我遇到的所有伟大的人
long ways
很长的路
and by the the opportunity i was given
借着我得到的机会
to
到
to be successful way beyond my wildest
取得超越我最疯狂的成功
dreams when i first took here as a
当我第一次来到这里时的梦想
immigrant not a penny and no nobody
移民没有一分钱也没有人
doesn't use speak the language
不使用说该语言
to be where i am today and so
成为我今天的样子
one thing that i always believed about
我一直相信的一件事
america
美国
is this i think america is not defined
我认为美国没有被定义吗
by geography it is not defined
地理上没有定义
by race it is not defined
种族没有定义
by culture not defined by religion
由文化而非宗教定义
america is defined by set of ideas and
美国是由一系列想法和
ideals
理想
anyone no matter your race religion
任何人，无论你的种族宗教信仰如何
culture background if you sign up to
文化背景如果您注册
that
那个
set of ideas ideals can be
一组想法理想可以是
america and i was one of those who
美国和我就是其中之一
believe in those ideas and ideas and it
相信那些想法和想法
becomes
变成
successful in america and i wanted that
在美国取得成功，我希望如此
experiment to really continue
实验真正继续
and obviously when you look at history
显然当你回顾历史时
it was
原来是
never a perfect experiment um and it was
从来都不是一个完美的实验，嗯，它是
often marked by
常被标记为
the cleansiness sometimes actually all
清洁有时实际上全部
right crew and malicious
正确的船员和恶意的
if you think about experiences with
如果你想到的经历
african-americans and all the other
非裔美国人和所有其他人
minorities
少数民族
but i think that america remains the
但我认为美国仍然是
only country on earth
地球上唯一的国家
so inspired and such constructed
如此受到启发和如此构建
and for that experiment to continue
为了让这个实验继续下去
it calls constantly to our better angels
它不断呼唤我们更好的天使
inside each one of us and to really
在我们每个人的内心深处
restrict the worst instincts of all of
限制所有人最坏的本能
us
我们
and throughout a different period of
并且在不同时期
time people need to rise up
人们需要站起来的时候了
to counter those worst instinct and
来对抗那些最糟糕的本能
fight them and
与他们战斗并
face them down and this is one of those
面对他们，这是其中之一
period
期间
again so i think the entire community
我再次认为整个社区
of asian americans have to come together
亚裔美国人必须走到一起
the entire
整个
american community need to really come
美国社区需要真正来
together to really fight
一起真正战斗
this wave of anti-asian discrimination
这波反亚裔歧视浪潮
so along with the uh a number of uh
所以连同呃一些呃
wonderful colleagues we are co-founding
我们共同创立的优秀同事
a new national organization
一个新的国家组织
whose mission is to serve asian
其使命是服务亚洲
americans
美国人
in their pursuit of belonging and
在他们追求归属感和
prosperity free from
繁荣自由
discrimination slander or violence
歧视、诽谤或暴力
and one of the things that our community
我们社区的一件事
needs is
需求是
is enormous amount of funding the
是数额巨大的资金
statistics tell us
统计数据告诉我们
that only 0.2
那只有0.2
of all philanthropy in america goes to
美国所有慈善事业都捐给了
asian-american causes and we want to
亚裔美国人的事业，我们希望
fundamentally change that
从根本上改变这一点
and hopefully with this new organization
希望通过这个新组织
new group of people
新的一群人
we really want to fundamentally change
我们真的想从根本上改变
that picture
那张照片
and the other thing is that with the
另一件事是
global economy the center of the global
全球经济是全球的中心
economy is shifting from the atlantic
经济正在从大西洋转移
ocean
海洋
to the pacific ocean asian-american
到太平洋 亚裔美国人
20 million strong are going to perform
2000万强者上演
i mean play a increasingly important
我的意思是发挥越来越重要的作用
role
角色
to position america as the new
将美国定位为新的
pacific economic power and that group of
太平洋经济强国和该集团
people more than other ones
人们比其他人多
if fully integrate as the very fabric
如果完全融入到织物中
of american society could help lead
美国社会可以帮助领导
america
美国
to better integrated with the rising
以便更好地融入新兴市场
economic ties in asia
亚洲经济联系
it's okay that's terrific it's a great
没关系，这太棒了，太棒了
note to end on unfortunately we have
请注意结束不幸的是我们有
two minutes left thank you very much
还剩两分钟，非常感谢
for this really encyclopedic and
对于这本真正的百科全书式的
enlightening talk
启发性的谈话
i think i have to turn it back over
我想我必须把它翻过来
however to the mc for the last two
然而最后两个主持人
minutes right
分钟右
okay because they're on the screen thank
好的，因为它们在屏幕上，谢谢
you very much
你非常
wow thank you it's always a pleasure
哇谢谢你总是很高兴
thank you for really having that class
谢谢你真的上这堂课
you know 28 years ago
你知道28年前
i wouldn't i wouldn't know what i'm
我不会 我不会知道我是什么
doing today so thank you
今天做的所以谢谢你
okay go ahead
好的，继续吧
hello vivian i think i'm turning that
你好，维维安，我想我正在改变这个
back to you
回到你身边
brilliant can you hear us thank you
太棒了，你能听到我们说话吗，谢谢
professor bruce greenward
布鲁斯·格林沃德教授
and mr lee lu for this valuable
以及李录先生的宝贵贡献
conversation
谈话
this marks the end of this year's
这标志着今年的结束
columbia china business conference
哥伦比亚中国商务会议
in these four days of discussion we have
在这四天的讨论中我们
taken a journey
旅行了
across various dimensions of china's
跨越中国的各个维度
amazing development
惊人的发展
and exciting future in an age of change
变革时代的美好未来
and opportunities our speakers have
以及我们的演讲者拥有的机会
given us a fascinating
给了我们一个令人着迷的
glimpse of what's to come on behalf of
一瞥即将发生的事情
columbia business school
哥伦比亚商学院
our conference team wants to express
我们的会议团队想要表达
sincere appreciation
真诚的赞赏
to all the guest speakers sponsors media
致所有演讲嘉宾赞助商媒体
partners
合作伙伴
and faculty of columbia business school
和哥伦比亚商学院的教师
this year's conference is generously
今年的大会盛况空前
sponsored by
赞助者
bank of china hayton international
中国银行海顿国际
securities
证券
tiger brokers johnson and johnson and
老虎经纪公司约翰逊和约翰逊
haito global
海通环球
we appreciate the support from our media
我们感谢媒体的支持
partners
合作伙伴
including yahoo finance senior finance
包括雅虎财经高级财务
tai chi maxine
太极玛克辛
barron's high social
巴伦的高社交
club tencent video sub china and many
俱乐部 腾讯视频 亚华等
more so lastly
最后更是如此
thank you audience around the world for
感谢世界各地的观众
your time and participation
您的时间和参与
live from columbia business school in
住在哥伦比亚商学院
new york city good morning and good
纽约市早上好，好
night and see you
晚上见
next year we finished exactly on time
明年我们准时完成
welcome to columbia business school the
欢迎来到哥伦比亚商学院
very center of business
非常商业中心
welcome to the next level of you the
欢迎来到下一个层次
columbia mba is more than just advancing
哥伦比亚 MBA 不仅仅是进步
your career
你的职业生涯
this is about honing your unique
这是为了磨练你的独特性
leadership style bringing your visions
领导风格带来您的愿景
to reality
到现实
and delivering them to the world you
并将它们传递给您的世界
will be the leader
将成为领导者
you want to be you will be able to walk
你想成为你就能走路
into a room any room
进入一个房间 任何房间
and solve welcome to new york the global
并解决全球欢迎来到纽约
business hub
商业中心
where startups get their start business
初创公司开始创业的地方
thrives and game changing strategy
蓬勃发展并改变游戏规则的策略
gets put into play you will have direct
投入使用你将直接
access to today's influencers
接触当今的影响者
the entrepreneurs of silicon alley the
硅巷企业家
wizards of wall street
华尔街奇才
the trendsetters of fashion avenue the
时尚大道的潮流引领者
agents of change
变革的推动者
welcome to a network a family of over 42
欢迎来到 42 岁以上家庭网络
000 alumni
000 名校友
let the collaboration begin this is not
让合作开始吧这不是
a sit
坐
and learn environment this is grab the
和学习环境这是抓住
reins and lead
缰绳和铅
you belong here
你属于这里
you
你